<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A treatise of monarchie, containing two parts: 1. concerning monarchy in generall. 2. concerning this particular monarchy.  Wherein all the maine questions occurrent in both, are stated, disputed, and determined: and in the close, the contention now in being, is moderately debated, and the readiest meanes of reconcilement proposed. Done by an earnest desirer of his countries peace.</title>
            <author>Hunton, Philip, 1604?-1682.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1643</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 191 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 43 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A86917</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H3781</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E103_15</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R5640</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99872875</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99872875</idno>
            <idno type="VID">155920</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A86917)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 155920)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 18:E103[15])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A treatise of monarchie, containing two parts: 1. concerning monarchy in generall. 2. concerning this particular monarchy.  Wherein all the maine questions occurrent in both, are stated, disputed, and determined: and in the close, the contention now in being, is moderately debated, and the readiest meanes of reconcilement proposed. Done by an earnest desirer of his countries peace.</title>
                  <author>Hunton, Philip, 1604?-1682.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 79, [1]p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for John Bellamy, and Ralph Smith, and are to be sold at the three golden Lions in Corn-hill,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno Dom. 1643.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to Philip Hunton.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "May 24th".</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Monarchy --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:155920:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:155920:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A TREATISE OF MONARCHIE, <hi>Containing two Parts:</hi>
               <list>
                  <item>1. Concerning Monarchy in generall.</item>
                  <item>2. Concerning this particular Monarchy.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Wherein all the maine Queſtions oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>current in both, are ſtated, diſputed, and determined:</p>
            <p>And in the cloſe, the Contention now in being, is moderately debated, and the readieſt meanes of Reconcilement propoſed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Done by an earneſt Deſirer of his Countries Peace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>John Bellamy,</hi> and <hi>Ralph Smith,</hi> and are to be ſold at the three golden Lions in Corn-hill.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anno Dom.</hi> 1643.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:155920:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:155920:2"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE:</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Write not this Diſcourſe to foment or heighten the wofull diſſention of the Kingdome; but if poſsible to cure, or at leaſt to allay it: That former too many have done already, this latter, much too few.</p>
            <p>When a Patient lies ſicke under the deſtroying pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roxiſmes of a Fever, every ſtander-by will be telling his Medicine, though he be no Phyſitian: O then let no Sonne of this State account it preſumption in me, for putting in my judgement, and ſpeaking that which I conceive might, if not remove, yet mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tigate this fatall diſtemperature of our common Mother: at another time perhaps it might be cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurable, but in this exigence laudable.</p>
            <p>Something I was full of, which I conceited might doe good; here I have produced it. And now if any man can finde a better way to appeaſement, for the ſake of peace let him ſpeedily declare it.</p>
            <p>I intend not theſe enſuing Diſputes to any high-flowne judgements, who looke downe on all mens, but their owne, to cenſure, not to be informed, nor
<pb facs="tcp:155920:3"/>
to any which hath deſignes of his owne, which on the opportunity of this Diviſion hee meanes to follow; nor to any who is already poſſeſſed by an opinion, which hee reſolves to make good: But to the calme and impartiall ſpirit of every judicious, peacefull man; Let him weigh my Aſſertions by my grounds on which I build them, and if he find them any where unſound, let him ſhew mee in what, and I will gladly and thankfully reforme my errour: For as I love not obſtinacy in groundleſſe opinions in others, ſo I would avoid it in my ſelfe.</p>
            <p>I have not annexed my <hi>Name,</hi> not that I am aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to owne what I conceive to be the truth; but becauſe I know who I am, and that my Name could adde no eſtimation to the Treatiſe: Nor do I deſire it ſhould: They who ſearch for Truth muſt regard <hi>Things,</hi> not <hi>Perſons:</hi> Give me therefore the now <hi>common Liberty</hi> to goe nameleſſe; many have taken it for worſe ends. If any condemn me for any thing here, it muſt be for endevouring a thankleſſe Moderation 'twixt two Extremes. But I will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine you no longer at the doore.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:155920:3"/>
            <head>The <hi>Contents</hi> of the enſuing <hi>Treatiſe.</hi>
            </head>
            <div n="1" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>Part. 1.</hi> Of Monarchy in generall.</head>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <label>Cap. 1.</label> Of Politicall Government.
<list>
                        <item>ITs Originall: How farre forth is is from God? <hi>Sect. 1.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Its end: whether the end of government be the peoples good? <hi>Sect. 2.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Its diviſion into ſeverall ſorts. <hi>Sect. 3.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <label>Cap. 2.</label> Of the diviſion of Monarchy into abſolute and limited.
<list>
                        <item>Whether abſolute Monarchy be a lawfull Government? <hi>Sect. 1.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Of three degrees of abſolutenes in Monarchy. <hi>Sect. 2.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Whether Reſiſtence be lawfull in abſolute Monarchy? <hi>Sect. 3.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>What it is which conſtituteth a Monarchy limited? <hi>Sect. 4.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>How farre ſubjection is due in a limited Monarchy? <hi>Sect. 5.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>How farre reſiſtence is lawfull in a limited Monarchy? <hi>Sect. 6.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Who ſhall be Iudge of the exceſſes of a limited Monarch? <hi>Sect. 7.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <label>Cap. 3.</label> Of the diviſion of Monarchy into elective and ſucceſſive.
<list>
                        <item>Elective and ſucceſſive Monarchies, what they are? <hi>Sect. 1.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Whether all Monarchy be originally from the peoples conſent? <hi>Sect. 2.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Of Monarchy by divine Inſtitution. <hi>Sect. 3.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Of Monarchy by preſcription. <hi>Sect. 4.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Of Monarchy by Conqueſt. <hi>Sect. 5.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Whether Conqueſt can give a juſt Title? <hi>Sect. 5.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Whether a ſucceſsive Monarch may not be alſo limited? <hi>Sect. 6.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <label>Cap. 4.</label> Of the diviſion of Monarchy into ſimple and mixed.
<list>
                        <item>Simple and mixed Monarchy what they are? <hi>Sect. 1.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>What it is which conſtituteth a Monarchy mixed? <hi>Sect. 2.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>How farre the Princes power extends in a mixed Monarchy? <hi>Sect. 3.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>Part 2.</hi> Of this particular Monarchy.</head>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <label>Cap. 1.</label>
                     <list>
                        <item>Whether the power wherewith our Kings be inveſted be an abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute or limited and moderated Power?</item>
                        <item>The Queſtion ſtated. <hi>Sect. 1.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Proved radically limited. <hi>Sect. 2.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <pb facs="tcp:155920:4"/>Contrary Arguments anſwered. <hi>Sect. 3. &amp; 4.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <label>Cap. 2.</label> Wherein and how this Monarchy is limited and defined?</item>
                  <item>
                     <label>Cap. 3.</label> Whether it be of a ſimple or mixed conſtitution?
<list>
                        <item>It is proved to be fundamentall mixed. <hi>Sect. 1.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>The Arguments for the contrary are anſwered. <hi>Sect. 2.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Whether the Authority of the two Houſes be ſubordinate and derived from the Kings? <hi>Sect. 3.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>The Queſtion reſolved and cleared. <hi>Sect. 4.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <label>Cap. 4.</label> How farre forth this Monarchy is mixed, and what part of the power is referred to a mixed ſubject?</item>
                  <item>
                     <label>Cap. 5.</label> How farre forth the two eſtates may oppoſe the Will and proceedings of the Monarch?
<list>
                        <item>The Queſtion duly ſtated. <hi>Sect. 1, 2.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Whether Reſiſtence of Inſtruments of illegall Commands be lawfull? <hi>Sect. 3.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Proved lawfull. <hi>Sect. 3.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Contrary Arguments diſſolved. <hi>Sect. 4.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <label>Cap. 6.</label>
                     <list>
                        <item>In what caſes the other Eſtates may aſſume the Armes of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome for reſiſtence of Inſtruments of arbitrary Commands? An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered negatively. <hi>Sect. 1.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Affirmatively. <hi>Sect. 2.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <label>Cap. 7.</label>
                     <list>
                        <item>Where the legall power of finall Iudging of theſe caſes doth reſide, the three eſtates differing about them?</item>
                        <item>The Queſtion is ſtated and determined. <hi>Sect. 1.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Arguments contrary are anſwered. <hi>Sect. 2.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>What to be done in ſuch diſſention. <hi>Sect. 3.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <label>Cap. 8.</label>
                     <list>
                        <item>The former Truths brought home to the preſent contention. <hi>Sect. 1.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>A moderate debate concerning the preſent contention. <hi>Sect. 2.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>The ſpeedieſt meanes of Reconcilement propoſed. <hi>Sect. 3.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </div>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:155920:4"/>
            <head>A TREATISE OF MONARCHIE.</head>
            <div n="1" type="part">
               <head>PART. I.</head>
               <div n="1" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CAP. I.</hi> Of Politicall Government, and its Diſtinction into ſeverall Kinds.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Overnment and Subjection are Relatives,<label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>1</label> ſo that what is ſaid of the One, may in proportion be ſaid of the other: Which being ſo, it will be needleſſe to treat of both: becauſe it will be eaſie to apply what is ſpoken of one to the other. Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment is <hi>Poteſtatis Exercitium,</hi> the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe of a Morall Power. One of theſe is the Root and Meaſure of the other; which if it exceed, is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orbitant, is not Government, but a Tranſgresſion of it. This Power and Government is differenced with reſpect to the Governed, to wit, a Family, which is called <hi>Oeconomicall:</hi> or a publike ſociety, which is called <hi>Politicall,</hi> or Magiſtracie. Concerning this Magiſtracie we will treat 1. in generall.
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:155920:5"/>
2. Of the principall kind of it.</p>
                  <p>In generall concerning Magiſtracie, There are two things about which I find difficultie and difference, <hi>viz.</hi> the Origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall, and the End.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Authority, how farre from God, how farre from Men.</note>Firſt for the Originall: There ſeem to be two extremes in Opinion; while ſome amplifie the Divinitie therof: Others ſpeak ſo ſlightly of it, as if there were little els but Humane Inſtitution in it. I will briefly lay down my apprehenſions of the evident truth in this point: and it may be, things being clearly and diſctinctly ſet down, there will be no reall ground for contrariety in this matter. Three things herein muſt neceſſarily be diſtinguiſhed, <hi>viz.</hi> 1. The Conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution of Power of Magiſtracie in generall. 2. The Limita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of it to this or that kind. 3. The Determination of it to this or that Individuall Perſon or Line.</p>
                  <p>For the firſt of theſe, 1. It is Gods expreſſe Ordinance that in the ſocieties of Mankind, there ſhould be a Magiſtracie or Government. At firſt when there were but two, God ordeyned it, <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.16. S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Paul</hi> affirmes as much of the Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers that be, none excepted, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13 1. 2 This Power where ever placed ought to be reſpected as a participation of divine Soveraignty, <hi>Pſal,</hi> 82.1.6. and every ſoule ought to be ſubject to it for the <hi>Lords ſake</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.13. that is, for conſcience ſake of Gods Ordinance, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.5. and under penaltie of Dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, <hi>v.</hi> 2. Theſe are Truths againſt which there is no co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour of oppoſition. Indeed this Power may be claymed by them who have it not; and where there is a limitation of this Power, ſubjection may be claymed in caſes which are without thoſe limits: But to this Ordinance of Power where it is, and when it requires ſubjection, it muſt be given; as before.</p>
                  <p>For the ſecond. 1. In ſome particular communities the Limitation of it to this or that kind, is an immediate Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of God: ſo Kingly Power was appointed to the Jewes on their deſire, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 8.9. whether they had not a kind of Monarchicall Government before, I will not ſtand on it: but it is evident that then, on their earneſt deſire God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe condeſcended to an eſtabliſhment of Regalitie in that
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:155920:5"/>
ſtate. 2. But for a generall binding Ordinance, God hath given no word, either to command or commend one kind above another: Men may according to their Relations to the forme they live under, to their affections and judgements in divers reſpects, preferre this or that form above the reſt; but we have no divine limitation: and it were an abſurditie to think ſo; for then we ſhould uncharitably condemne all the Communities which have not that form for violation of Gods Ordinance and pronounce thoſe other Powers unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full. 3. This then muſt have another and lower fountain to flow from, which can be no other then Humane. The higher Power is Gods Ordinance: That it reſideth in One, or more; in ſuch or ſuch a way is from humane deſignment: for when God leaves a matter indifferent, the reſtriction of this indifferencie is left to ſecondary cauſes. And I conceive this is <hi>S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. Peters</hi> meaning, when he calls Magiſtracie <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, Humane Creature; S. <hi>Paul</hi> calls it <hi>Gods Ordinance,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Power is <hi>Gods: S. Peter</hi> calls it humane Ordinance, becauſe the ſpecification of it to this or that form, is from the ſocieties of Mankind. I confeſſe it may be called a hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Creature, in regard of its ſubject, which is a Man, or Men: or its End which is to rule over Men for the good of Men, but the other ſeems more naturall and it induces no diſparagement to Authority, being ſo underſtood. But how ever you take that place, yet the thing affirmed ſtands good, that God by no word binds any people to this or that form, till they by their own Act bind themſelves.</p>
                  <p>For the third: the ſame is to be ſaid of it, as of the ſecond: ſome particular men we find whom God was pleaſed by his own immediate choiſe to inveſt with this his Ordinance of Authority: <hi>Moſes, Saul, David,</hi> yea God by his immediate Ordinance determined the Government of that people to <hi>Davids</hi> poſteritie and made it ſuccesſive; ſo that that People after his appointment and word was made known to them, and the room voyd by <hi>Sauls</hi> death, was as immediately bound by divine Law to have <hi>David,</hi> and his Sonnes after him to be Magiſtrates, as to Magiſtracie it ſelfe. But God hath not done ſo for every people: <hi>aſcriptum eſt</hi> cannot be alledged for
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:155920:6"/>
the endowing this or that perſon or ſtock with Soveraignty over a community: They alone had the priviledge of an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary Word. All others have the ordinary and medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate hand of God to enthrone them: They attaine this deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination of Authority to their Perſons by the tacite and virtuall, or elſe expreſſe and formall conſent of that Society of men they governe, either in their owne perſons, or the root of their ſucceſsion, as I doubt not, in the ſequele it will be made appeare. But let no man thinke that it is any leſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning or weakning of Gods Ordinance in them, to teach that it is annexed to their Perſons by a humane Meane: for though it be not ſo full a title to come to it by them ſimple Providence of God, as by the expreſſe Precept of God: yet when by the diſpoſing hand of Gods Providence a Right is conveyed to a perſon or family, by the meanes of a publique Fundamentall Oath, Contract and Agreement of a State, it is equivalent then to a Divine Word; and within the bounds of that publique Agreement the conveyed Power is as <hi>Obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatory,</hi> as if an immediate word had deſigned it. Thus it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears that they which ſay there is <hi>divinum quiddam</hi> in Sover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aignes, and that they have their power from God, ſpeake in ſome ſence truth; As alſo they which ſay that originally Power is in the People, may in a ſound ſence be underſtood. And in theſe things we have Dr. <hi>Ferns</hi> conſent in his late diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe upon this ſubject. <hi>Sect.</hi> 3.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>2</label> For the end of Magiſtracie; to ſet out that is no hard matter,<note place="margin">Whether the end of Government be the peoples good?</note> if we conſider what was looked at when God ordey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned it. That was the Good of the ſociety of men over which it is ſet: So Saint <hi>Paul, Rom.</hi> 13.4. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. God aymed at it in the Inſtitution of Government: and ſo do all men in the choice of it, where they may be chooſers: ſuch a Government, and ſuch perſons to ſway it, as may moſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce to publique Weale. Alſo it is the meaſure of all the Acts of the Governour: and he is good or bad according as he uſes his Power to the good of the State wherewith he is intruſted. That is the end: but not the ſole end; The preſervation of the Power and Honour of the Governour
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:155920:6"/>
is an end too: but I thinke not co-ordinate, but ſubordinate to the other: becauſe doubtles in the Conſtitution of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that is firſt thought on, and this in congruity to that; Alſo the reaſon why the Power and Honour of the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate muſt be preſerved, is for the publique ſocieties ſake be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe its welfare depends thereon: And if it fall out that one of them muſt ſuffer: every good Magiſtrate will deſcend ſomething from his greatnes be it for the good of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munity: On the other ſide, though every ſubject ought for the honour and good of the Magiſtrate to give up his private; yet none ought to advance the greatnes of his Soveraign with the publique detriment. Whence in my apprehenſion the end of Magiſtracie is the good of the whole Body, Head, and Members conjunctly: but if we ſpeak <hi>diviſim,</hi> then the good of the Society is the Ultime end: and next to that, as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducent to that, the Governours Greatnes and Prerogative. And herein alſo accordeth Dr. <hi>Fern</hi> with us. <hi>Sect.</hi> 3. Where he ſayes, That the people are the end of the governing Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er. There is another queſtion of mainer concernment, here in our generall diſcourſe of Authority fitly to be handled. <hi>viz.</hi> How farre ſubjection is due to it? but becauſe it hath a great dependance on the kinds and States of Power, and can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be ſo well conceived without the Precognition there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of: I will referre it to after opportunities.</p>
                  <p>For the diviſion of this Power of Magiſtracie. It cannot <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>3</label> be well divided into ſeveral ſpecies;<note place="margin">Diviſion of Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtracie.</note> for it is one ſimple thing an indiviſible bcame of Divine Perfection; yet for our more diſtinct conceaving thereof. Men have framed ſeverall di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinctions of it. So with reſpect of its meaſure, it is abſolute or limited: In reſpect of its manner. It is as St. <hi>Peter</hi> divides it, Supreame, or Subordinate. In reſpect of its Meane of ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiring it is Elective, or ſucceſsive; for I conceive that of Conqueſt, and Preſcription of uſuage are reducible to one of theſe, as will appeare afterwards. In reſpect of its degrees it is <hi>Nomotheticall</hi> or <hi>Architectonicall</hi> and <hi>Gubernative</hi> or <hi>Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutive.</hi> And in reſpect of the ſubject of its reſidence there is an ancient and uſuall diſtinction of it into <hi>Monarchicall, Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtocraticall</hi>
                     <pb n="6" facs="tcp:155920:7"/>
and <hi>Democraticall.</hi> Theſe either ſimple or mixt of two, or all three together, of which the <hi>Predominant</hi> gives the denomination. Theſe are not <hi>accurate ſpecificative,</hi> Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of Power, for it admits none ſuch, but partitions of it according to divers reſpects. The courſe of my intention di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rects me to ſpeak only of <hi>Monarchicall</hi> Power, which is the chiefe and moſt uſuall forme of Government in the world; The other two being apt to reſolve into this, but this not ſo apt to diſſolve into them.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. II.</hi> Of the Diviſion of Monarchy into abſolute and limited.</head>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>1</label> NOW we muſt know that moſt of thoſe diſtinctions which were applyed to Power in generall are applia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to Monarchy: becauſe the reſpects on which they ariſe are to be found in it. But I will inſiſt on the three main diviſions: for the handling of them will bring us to a cleare underſtanding of what is needfull to be known about <hi>Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chicall</hi> Power.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, of the diſtinction of <hi>Monarchy</hi> into Abſolute and Limited. Abſolute <hi>Monarchy</hi> is when the Soveraignty is ſo fully in one, that it hath no Limits or Bounds under God, but his owne Will. It is when a people are abſolutely reſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned up or reſigne up themſelves to be governed by the will of one man. Such were the ancient <hi>Eaſterne Monarchies,</hi> and that of the <hi>Perſian</hi> and <hi>Turke</hi> at this day, as farre as we know. This is a lawfull Government and therefore where men put themſelves into this utmoſt degree of ſubjection by <hi>Oath</hi> and Contract,<note place="margin">Whether abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute Monarchy be a lawfull go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment.</note> or are borne and brought unto it by Gods Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, it binds them and they muſt abide it<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> becauſe an <hi>Oath</hi> to a lawfull thing is <hi>Obligatory.</hi> This in Scripture is very evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent as <hi>Ezek.</hi> 17 16.18.19. Where Iudgement is denoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced againſt the King of <hi>Iudah</hi> for breaking the Oath made to
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:155920:7"/>
the King of <hi>Babylon;</hi> and it is called Gods Oath, yet doubtles this was an Oath of abſolute ſubjection. And <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. the power which then was, was abſolute; yet the Apoſtle not excluding it; calls it <hi>Gods ordinance,</hi> and commands ſubjecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to it: ſo Chriſt commands tribute to be paid, and payes it himſelfe; yet it was an arbitrary taxe, the production of an abſolute power. Alſo the ſoveraignty of maſters over ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants was abſolute, and the ſame in Oeconomy as abſolute Monarchy is in policie, yet the Apoſtle enjoynes not ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters called to Chriſtianity to renounce that title as too great and rigid to be kept but exhorts them to moderation in the exerciſe of it; and ſervants to remaine contented in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of their ſervitude. More might be ſaid to legitimate this kinde of governement, but it needs not in ſo plaine a caſe.</p>
                  <p>This abſolute Monarchy hath three degrees, yet all with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>2</label> the ſtate of abſoluteneſſe. The firſt, when the Monarch,<note place="margin">Three degrees of abſoluteneſſe.</note> whoſe will is the peoples Law, doth ſet himſelfe no ſtated Rule or Law to rule by, but by immediate Edicts and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands of his owne will governes them, as in his owne and Councels judgement he thinks fit. Secondly, when he ſets downe a Rule and Law by which he will ordinarily govern, reſerving to himſelfe liberty to vary from it, wherein, and as oft as in his diſcretion he judges fit: and in this the Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne is as free as the former, onely the people are at a more certainty what he expects from them in ordinary. Thirdly, when he not onely ſets downe an expreſſe Rule and Law to governe by, but alſo promiſeth and engages himſelf in many caſes not to alter that rule: but this engagement is an after condeſcent and act of grace, not diſſolving the abſolute oath of ſubiection, which went before it, nor is intended to be the rule of his power, but of the exerciſe of it. This Ruler is not ſo abſolute as the former in the uſe of his power, for he hath put a bond on that, which he cannot breake without breach of promiſe; that is, without ſin: but he is as abſolute in his power, if he will ſinfully put it forth into act, it hath no politick bounds, for the people ſtill owe him abſolute
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:155920:8"/>
ſubiection, that not being diſſolved or leſſened by an act of grace comming afterwards.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>3</label> Now in governments of this nature, How far obedience is due,<note place="margin">Whether reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance be law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full in abſo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lute Monarchy.</note> and, Whether any reſiſtance be lawfull, is a queſtion which here muſt be decided. For the due effecting whereof, we muſt premiſe ſome needfull diſtinctions to avoid confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion. Obedience is twofold; firſt, Poſitive and active, when in conſcience of an authority we doe the thing commanded: ſecondly, Negative and paſſive, when though we anſwer not Authority by doing, yet we doe it by contented undergoing the penalty impoſed. Proportionably reſiſtance is twofold: firſt, Poſitive, by an oppoſing of force: ſecondly, Negative, when onely ſo much is done as may defend our ſelves from force, without returne of force againſt the Aſſailant. Now this negative reſiſtance is alſo twofold: firſt, In inferiour and ſufferable caſes: ſecondly, or in the ſupreme caſe and laſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of life and death: and then too it is firſt, either of par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular perſon or perſons; ſecondly, or of the whole com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munity. And if of particular perſons, then either under plea and pretence of equity aſſaulted; or elſe without any plea at all, meerly for will and pleaſure ſake: for to that degree of rage and cruelty ſometimes the heart of man is given over. All theſe are very diſtinguiſhable caſes, and will be of uſe either in this or the enſuing diſputes.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Aſſert. </seg>1</label> To the queſtion I ſay, Firſt, Poſitive obedience is abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely due to the will and pleaſure of an abſolute Monarch, in all lawfull and indifferent things: becauſe in ſuch a State the will of the Prince is the ſupreme Law, ſo that it binds to obedience in every thing not prohibited by a ſuperiour, that is, Divine Law: for it is in ſuch caſe the higher power, and is Gods ordinance.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Aſſert. </seg>2</label> Secondly, When the will of an abſolute Monarch com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands a thing forbidden to be done by Gods Law then it bindes not to active obedience; then is the Apoſtles rule un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly true, <hi>It is better to obey God then men:</hi> For the Law of the inferiour gives place to the ſuperiour. In things defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by God, it ſhould be all one with us for the Magiſtrate
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:155920:8"/>
to command us to tranſgreſſe that, as to command us an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſibility; and impoſsibilities fall under no Law. But on this ground no man muſt quarrell with Authoritie, or reject its commands as unlawfull, unleſſe there be an open unlawful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in the face of the act commanded. For if the unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe be hidden in the ground or reaſon of the action, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriours muſt not be curious to enquire into the grounds or reaſons of the commands of ſuperiours; for ſuch licence of enquiry would often fruſtrate great undertakings, which much depend on ſpeed and ſecrecy of execution. I ſpeak all this of abſolute government, where the will and reaſon of the Monarch is made the higher power, and its expreſſion the ſupreme Law of a State.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, ſuppoſe an abſolute Monarch ſhould ſo degene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Aſſert. </seg>3</label> into Monſtrous unnaturall Tyranny, as apparently to ſeeke the deſtruction of the whole community, ſubject to him in the loweſt degree of vaſſallage, then ſuch a commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity may negatively reſiſt ſuch ſubverſion: yea, and if con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained to it by the laſt neceſſity, poſitively reſiſt and defend themſelves by force againſt any inſtruments whatſoever, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed for the effecting thereof. 1. <hi>David</hi> did ſo in his parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular caſe, when purſued by <hi>Saul:</hi> he made negative reſiſtence by flight, and doubtleſſe he intended poſitive reſiſtence a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt any inſtrument, if the negative would not have ſerved the turne: elſe why did he ſo ſtrengthen himſelfe by Forces? ſure not to make poſitive reſiſtance, and lay violent hands upon the Perſon of the Lords Anointed, as it appeared; yet for ſome reaſon he did it doubtleſſe, which could be none o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, but by that force of Armes to defend himſelfe againſt the violence of any miſ-imployed inferiour hands. If then he might doe it for his particular ſafety, much rather may it be done for the publike. 2. Such an act is without the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe of any the moſt abſolute Potentate; and therefore to reſiſt in it, can be to reſiſt no power, nor the violation of any due of ſubjection. For, firſt, the moſt ſubmiſſe ſubjection ever intended by any community, when they put themſelves under anothers power, was the command of a reaſonable will and power; but to will and command the deſtruction of
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:155920:9"/>
the whole body over which a power is placed, were an act of will moſt unreaſonable and ſelf-deſtructive, and ſo not the act of ſuch a will, to which ſubjection was intended by any reaſonable creatures. Secondly the publike good and being is armed at in the utmoſt bond of ſubjection; for in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution of ſuch unlimited ſoveraignty, though every parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular mans good and being is ſubjected to the will of One ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme yet certainly the conſervation of the whole Publike was intended by it; which being invaded; the intent of the conſtitution is overthrowne and an act is done which can be ſuppoſed to be within the compaſſe of no politicall power: So that did <hi>Nero</hi> as it was reported of him in his im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manity thirſt for the deſtruction of whole <hi>Rome;</hi> and if he were truly what the Senate pronounced him to be, <hi>Humani generis hoſtis,</hi> then it might juſtifie a negative reſiſtance of his perſon; and a poſitive, of any Agent ſhould be ſet on ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>humane a ſervice. And the united Provinces are allowed in reſiſting <hi>Philip</hi> 2<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. though he had bin their abſolute Monarch, if he reſolved the extirpation of the whole people, and the planting the countrey with <hi>Spaniards,</hi> as it is reported he did. And that aſſertion of ſome, that <hi>All</hi> reſiſtance is againſt the Apoſtles prohibition. Reſiſtance by power of Armes is ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly unlawfull, cannot be juſtified in ſuch a latitude. But of this more will be ſpoken in the current of this diſcourſe.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Aſſert. </seg>4</label> Fourthly, ſuppoſe by ſuch a power any particular perſon or perſons life be invaded, without any plea of reaſon or cauſe for it, I ſuppoſe it hard to deny him liberty of negative reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of power; yea, and poſitive, of any Agents, in ſuch aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſault of murther: for though the caſe be not ſo cleare as the former yet it ſeemes to me juſtified by the fact of <hi>David,</hi> and the reſcuing of <hi>Jonathan</hi> from the cauſleſſe cruell intent of his Fathers putting him to death. As alſo ſuch an act of will carrying no colour of reaſon with it, cannot be eſteem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the act of a rationall will, and ſo no will intended to be the Law of Soveraignty. Not that I thinke a Monarch of ſuch abſoluteneſſe is bound to yeeld a reaſon why he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands any man to be put to death, before his command be obeyed; but I conceive the perſon ſo commanded to
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:155920:9"/>
death may bee juſtified before God and men for prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting himſelfe by eſcape, or otherwiſe, unleſſe ſome reaſon or cauſe bee made knowne to him of ſuch com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand.</p>
                  <p>Fifthly, Perſons ſubject to an unlimited dominion muſt <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Aſſert. </seg>5</label> without reſiſtance ſubject their Eſtates, Liberties, Perſons, to the will and pleaſure of their Lord, ſo it carry any plea or ſhew of reaſon and equity. Firſt, it ſeemes to me evident, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.18, 19 20. if well doing be miſtaken by the reaſon and judgement of the power for ill doing, and we be puni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed for it, yet the Magiſtrate going according to his miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guided reaſon it is the command of a reaſonable will, and ſo to be ſubmitted to; becauſe ſuch a one ſuffers by Law, in a State where the Lords will is the Law. Secondly, In com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands of the power where is the plea of reaſon and equity on the part of the commander, whether it be ſuch indeed, ſome power muſt judge, but the conſtitution of abſolute Monarchy reſolves all judgement into the will of the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narch, as the ſupreme Law: ſo that if his will judicially cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure it juſt it muſt be yeelded to as if it were juſt without repeale or redreſſement by any created power. And let none complaine of this as a hard condition, when they or their Anceſtors have ſubjected themſelves to ſuch a power by oath, or politicall contract: If it be Gods ordinance to ſuch, it muſt be ſubjected to and its exorbitances born, as he ſayes in <hi>Tac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>tu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>,</hi> as men beare famine, peſtilence, and other effects of Gods diſpleaſure.</p>
                  <p>Sixthly in abſolute Monarchy the perſon of the Monarch <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Aſſert. </seg>6</label> is above the reach of juſt force and poſitive reſiſtance: for ſuch a full reſignation of mens ſelves to his will and power, by the irrevocable oath and bond of politicall contract, doth make the perſon as ſacred as the Unction of <hi>Saul</hi> or <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid.</hi> In ſuch a State all lawful power is below him, ſo that he is uncapable of any penall hand which muſt be from a ſupe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour, or it is uniuſt. I have bin the longer on this abſolute Monarchy, becauſe though it doth not concerne us, yet it will give light to the ſtating of doubts in governments of a more reſtrained nature: for what is true here in the full ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:155920:10"/>
of power, is there alſo as true within the compaſſe of their power.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>4</label> In moderate or limited Monarchy it is an enquiry of ſome weight to know,<note place="margin">What makes a Monarchy li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mited?</note> 
                     <hi>What it is which conſtitutes it in the ſtate of a li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mited Monarchy.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Firſt, A Monarchy may be ſtinted in the exerciſe of its <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Aſſert. </seg>1</label> power, and yet be an abſolute Monarchy, as appeared before in our diſtinction of abſolute Monarchy: If that bounds be a ſubſequent act, and proceeding from free will and grace in the Monarch; for it is not the exerciſe, but the nature and meaſure of power, wherewith he is radically inveſted, which denominates him a free, or conditionate Monarch.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Aſſert. </seg>2</label> Secondly, I take it, that a limited Monarch muſt have his bounds of power <hi>ab externo,</hi> not from the free determination of his owne will. And now Kings have not divine words and binding Lawes to conſtitute them in their Soveraignty, but derive it from ordinary providence, the ſole meane hereof is the conſent and fundamentall contract of a Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of men, which conſent puts them in their power, which can be no more nor other then is conveyed to them by ſuch contract of ſubiection, This is the root of all ſoveraignty individuated and exiſtent in this or that perſon or family; till this come and lift him up he is a private man, not diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring in ſtate from the reſt of his brethren; but then he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes another man, his perſon is ſacred by that ſoveraignty conveyed to it, which is Gods ordinance and image. The truth hereof will be more fully diſcovered, when we come to ſpeake of Elective and Succeſſive Monarchy.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Aſſert. </seg>3</label> Thirdly He is then a limited Monarch, who hath a Law beſide his owne will for the meaſure of his power. Firſt, the ſupreme power of the State muſt be in him, ſo that his power muſt not be limited by any power above his; for then hee were not a Monarch, but a ſubordinate magiſtrate. Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, this ſupreme power muſt be reſtrained by ſome Law, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to which this power was given, and by direction of which this power muſt act; elſe he were not a limited Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narch, that is, a liege Soveraigne, or legall King. Now a So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraignty
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:155920:10"/>
comes thus to be legall, or defined to a rule of Law, either by originall conſtitution, or by after-condeſcent. By originall conſtitution, when the ſociety publike conferres on one man a power by limited contract, reſigning them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to his government by ſuch a Law, reſerving to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves ſuch immunities: In this caſe, they which at firſt had power over themſelves, had power to ſet their owne termes of ſubiection; and hee which hath no title of power over them but by their act, can <hi>de jure</hi> have no greater then what is put over to him by that act By after-condeſcent, <hi>viz.</hi> when a Lord, who by conqueſt, or other right, hath an abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute arbitrary power; but not liking to hold by ſuch a right, doth either formally or virtually deſert it, and take a new legall right as judging it more ſafe for him to hold by, and deſirable of the people to be governed by. This is equivalent to that by originall conſtitution; yea, is all one with it: for this is in that reſpect a ſecondary originall conſtitution. But if it be objected, that this being a voluntary condeſcent is an act of grace, and ſo doth not derogate from his former abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luteneſſe as was ſaid before of an abſolute Monarch, who confines himſelfe to governe by one rule; I anſwer. This differs eſſentially from that: for there, a free Lord, of grace yeelds to rule by ſuch a Law, reſerving the fulneſſe of pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and ſtill requiring of the people a bond and oath of ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt indefinite ſubjection; ſo that it amounts not to a limi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of radicall power: whereas here is a change of title, and a reſolution to be ſubiected to, in no other way, then ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to ſuch a frame of government; and accordingly no other bond or oath of allegeance is required, or taken, then according to ſuch a Law: this amounts to a limitation of ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicall power. And therefore they ſpeak too generally, who affirme of all acts of grace proceeding from Princes to peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, as if they did not limit abſoluteneſſe: 'Tis true of acts of grace of that firſt kinde; but yet you ſee, an act of grace may be ſuch a one, as may amount to a reſignation of that abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luteneſſe into a more milde and moderate power unleſſe we ſhould hold it out of the power of an abſolute Lord to be o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; or that by free condeſcent, and act of grace, a man can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:155920:11"/>
as well part with, or exchange his right and title to a thing, as define himſelfe in the uſe and exerciſe; which I thinke none will affirme.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>5</label> In all Governments of this allay and legall Conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion there are three Queſtions of ſpeciall moment to be conſidered.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">How farre ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> is due in a limited Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy?</note>Firſt, How farre ſubjection is due? As farre as they are Gods Ordinance, as farre as they are a power and they are a power as farre as the Contract fundamentall from which un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der God their authority is derived doth extend. As abſolute Lords muſt be obeyed as farre as their Will enjoynes, becauſe their Will is the meaſure of their Power, and their ſubjects Law: ſo theſe in the utmoſt extent of the Law of the Land, which is the meaſure of their power, and their ſubjects duty of obedience. I ſay ſo farre, but I doe not ſay no further: for I believe, though on our former grounds it clearely fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes that ſuch Authority tranſcends its bounds if it com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand beyond the Law: and the Subject legally is not bound to ſubjection in ſuch caſe, yet in Conſcience a Subject is bound to yeeld to the Magiſtrate, even when he cannot <hi>de jure,</hi> challenge obedience, to prevent ſcandall or any occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of ſlighting the power which may ſometimes grow, even upon a juſt refuſall: I ſay, for theſe cauſes a ſubject ought not to uſe his liberty, but <hi>morem gerere,</hi> if it be in a thing in which he can poſsibly without ſubverſion, and in which his act may not be made a leading caſe, and ſo bring on a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription againſt publique Liberty.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>6</label>
                     <note place="margin">How farre it is Lawfull to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt</note>Secondly, how farre it is lawfull to reſiſt the exorbitant Illegal Commands of ſuch a Monarch? 1. As before in light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er caſes, in which it may be done, for the reaſons alledged, <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Poſ. </seg>1</label> and for the ſake of publique peace, we ought to ſubmit, and make no reſiſtance at all, but <hi>de jure recedere.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Poſ. </seg>2</label> 2. In caſes of higher nature. Paſsive reſiſtance, <hi>viz.</hi> By ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peale to Law, by Concealment, by Flight, is lawfull to be made, becauſe ſuch a Command is politically powerles, it proceeds not from Gods Ordinance in him: and ſo we ſin
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:155920:11"/>
not againſt Gods Ordinance in ſuch Non-ſubmiſsion, or Negative reſiſtance.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. For Inſtruments or Agents in ſuch commands, if the <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Poſ. </seg>3</label> ſtreight be ſuch, and a man be ſurprized, that no place is left for an appeale nor evaſion by Negative reſiſtance; I conceive, againſt ſuch. Poſitive reſiſtence may be made: becauſe au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority failing or this Act in the Supreame Power, the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent or Inſtrument can have none derived to him; and ſo is but in the nature of a private perſon, and his Act, as an offer of private violence, and ſo comes under the ſame rules for oppoſition.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. For the perſon of the Soveraigne, I conceive it, aſwell <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Poſ. </seg>4</label> above any Poſitive Reſiſtence, as the Perſon of an abſolute Monarch; Yea, though by the whole Community, (except there be an expreſſe reſervation of Power in the body of the State, or any deputed Perſons or Court, to uſe in caſe of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tolerable exorbitance. Poſitive Reſiſtence, which, if there be, then ſuch a Governour is no Monarch, for that Funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentall Reſervation deſtroyes it's being a Monarchy in aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as the Supreame Power is not in one.) For where e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver there is a Soveraigne Politique Power conſtituted, the perſon or perſons who are inveſted with it are Sacred, and out of the reach of Poſitive Reſiſtance or Violence: which, as I ſaid, if juſt, muſt be from no inferior or ſubordinate hand. But it will be objected, that ſith every Monarch hath his power from the conſent of the whole body, that conſent of the whole Body hath a Power above the Power of the Monarch, and ſo the reſiſtance which is done by it, is not by an inferior power and to this purpoſe is brought that Ax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iome. <hi>Quicquia efficit tale eſt magis tale.</hi> I anſwer, That rule even in naturall cauſes is lyable to abundance of reſtrictions: And in the particular in hand it holds not. Where the cauſe doth bereave himſelfe of that perfection by which it works, in the very act of cauſing, and convey it to that effect, It doth not remain more ſuch then the effect, but much leſſe, and below it, as if I convey an eſtate of Land to another, it doth not hold that after ſuch conveyance I have a better E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate remayning in me then that other, but rather the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary;
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:155920:12"/>
becauſe what was in one is paſſed to the other: The Servant who at the year of <hi>Iubile</hi> would not go out free, but have his eare boared, and given his Maſter a full Lordſhip o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver him: can we argue, that he had afterward more power over himſelfe then his Maſter, becauſe he gave his Maſter that power over him, by that act of Oeconomicall Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract. Thus the Community whoſe conſent eſtabliſhes a Power over them cannot be ſaid univerſally to have an emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nencie of Power above that which they conſtitute; ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times they have, ſometimes they have not: and to judge when they have, when not reſpect muſt be had to the Origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginall Contract and Fundamentall Conſtitution of that State, if they have conſtituted a Monarchy, that is, inveſted one man with the Soveraignty of Power, and ſubjected all the reſt to him; Then it were unreaſonable to ſay, they yet have it in themſelves; Or have a power of recalling that Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>premacie which by Oath and Contract they themſelves transferred on another: Unles we make this Oath and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract leſſe binding then private ones, diſſoluble at pleaſure, and ſo all Monarchs Tenants at will from their people. But if they in ſuch Conſtitution reſerve a power in the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to oppoſe and diſplace the Magiſtrate for exorbitancies, and reſerve to themſelves a Tribunall to trie him in, that man is not a Monarch but the Officer and Subſtitute of him or them to whom ſuch Power over him is reſerved or conferred. The Iſſue is this, If he be a Monarch he hath the <hi>Apex</hi> or <hi>Culmen Poteſtatis,</hi> and all his Subjects <hi>diviſim</hi> and <hi>conjunction,</hi> are below him: They have deveſted themſelves of all ſuperiority and no Power left for a Poſitive Oppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Perſon of him whom they have inveſted.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>7</label> Thirdly, Who ſhall be the Iudge of the Exceſſes of the Soveraigne Lord in Monarchies of this compoſure?<note place="margin">Who ſhall be the Iudge of the exceſſes of the Monarch?</note> I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, A frame of Government cannot be imagined of that perfection but that ſome inconveniencies there will be poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible for which there can be provided no remedie: Many miſeries to which a people under an abſolute Monarchie are lyable are prevented by this Legall Allay and definement of
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:155920:12"/>
Power. But this is expoſed to one defect from which that is free, that is an impoſsibility of conſtituting a Judge to deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine this laſt controverſie, <hi>viz.</hi> the Soveraignes tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing his fundamentall limits. This Judge muſt be either ſome Forraigner, and then <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>e loſe the freedome of the State, by ſubjecting it to an externall power in the greateſt caſe: or elſe within the body: If ſo then 1. either the Monarch himſelfe, and then you deſtroy the frame of the State, and make it ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute; for to define a Power to a Law, and then to make him Judge of his Deviations from that Law, is to abſolve him from all Law. Or elſe 2. the Community and their Deputies muſt have this power: and then, as before, you put the <hi>apex Poteſtatis,</hi> the <hi>prime</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> in the whole body, or a part of it, and deſtroy the being of Monarchy: The Ruler not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Gods immediate Miniſter but of that Power, be it where it will to which he is accomptable for his actions. So that I conceive in a limited legall Monarchy, there can be no ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted internall Judge of the Monarchs actions, if there grow a fundamentall Variance betwixt him and the Community. But you will ſay, It is all one way to abſoluteneſſe to aſsigne him no Judge as to make him his own Judge. <hi>Anſw.</hi> I ſay not ſimplie in this caſe there is no Judge: But that there can be no Judg legall and conſtituted within that frame of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: but it is a tranſcendent caſe beyond the proviſion of that Government, and muſt have an extraordinary Judge, and way of deviſion.</p>
                  <p>In this great and difficult caſe, I will deliver my appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſions freely and clearly, ſubmitting them to the cenſure of better Iudgements. Suppoſe the controverſie to happen in a Government fundamentally legall, and the people no further ſubjected then to Government by ſuch a Law.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. If the act in which the exorbitance and tranſgreſsion <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Poſ. </seg>1</label> is ſuppoſed to be, be of leſſer moment, and not ſtriking at the very being of that Government, it ought to be borne by publique patience, rather then to endanger the being of the State by a contention betwixt the head and body Politique.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. If it be mortall and ſuch as ſuffered, diſſolves the frame <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Poſ. </seg>2</label> and life of the Government and publique liberty. Then the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:155920:13"/>
illegality and deſtructive nature is to be ſet open and redreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſought by Petition; which if failing, Prevention by reſiſtance ought to be. But firſt that it is ſuch muſt be made apparent; and if it be apparent, and an Appeale made <hi>ad con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcientiam generis humani,</hi> eſpecially of thoſe of that Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, then the fundamentall Lawes of that Monarchy muſt iudge and pronounce the ſentence in every mans conſcience; and every man (as farre as concernes him) muſt follow the evidence of Truth in his owne ſoule, to oppoſe, or not op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, according as he can in conſcience acquit or condemne the act of carriage of the Governour. For I conceive in a Caſe which tranſcends the frame and proviſion of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment they are bound to. People are unbound, and in ſtate as if they had no Government; and the ſuperiour Law of Reaſon and Conſcience muſt be Judge: wherein every one muſt proceed with the utmoſt advice and impartiality: For if hee erre in iudgement hee either reſiſts Gods Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, or puts his hand to the ſubverſion of the State and Policy he lives in.</p>
                  <p>And this power of judging argues not a ſuperiority in thoſe who Judge, over him who is Judged for it is not Authoritative and Civill, but morall, reſiding in reaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Creatures and lawfull for them to execute, becauſe never deveſted and put off by any act in the conſtitution of a legall Government, but rather the reſervation of it intended: For when they define the Superiour to a Law, and conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute no Power to Judge of his Exceſſes from that Law, it is evident they reſerve to themſelves, not a Formall Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritative Power, but a morall Power, ſuch as they had originally before the Conſtitution of the Government; which muſt needs remaine, being not conveyed away in the Conſtitution.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="chapter">
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:155920:13"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. III.</hi> Of the diviſion of Monarchy into Elective and Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſive.</head>
                  <p>THe ſecond diviſion of Monarchy, which I intend to <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>1</label> treat of, is that of Elective or Succeſſive.<note place="margin">Elective and ſucceſsive Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy what they are?</note> Elective Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy is that, where by the fundamentall conſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the State, the ſupreme power is conveyed but to the perſon of him whom they take for their Prince; the people reſerving to themſelves power, by men deputed by the ſame conſtitution to elect a new perſon on the deceaſe of the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer. Succeſſive is, where by the fundamentall conſtitution of the State, the Soveraignty is conferred on one Prince; and in that one, as a root and beginning to his heires, after a forme and line of ſucceſſion, conſtituted alſo by the funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentals of that Government. In the firſt, the Peoples oath and contract of ſubiection extends but to one perſon: In the other, to the whole Race and Line of Succeſſors; which continuing, the bond of ſubjection continues; or which failing, the people returne to their firſt liberty, of chooſing a new perſon, or ſucceſſion to be inveſted with Soveraignty.</p>
                  <p>I doe conceive that in the firſt originall all Monarchy, yea <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>2</label> any individuall frame of Government whatſoever,<note place="margin">All Monarchy whether origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally from con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent?</note> is ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive: that is, is conſtituted, and drawes its force and right from the conſent and choice of that Community over which it ſwayeth. And that triple diſtinction of Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy in o that which is gotten by Conqueſt, Preſcription, or Choice is, not of diſtinct parts unleſſe by Choice be meant full and formall Choice: my reaſon is, becauſe man being a voluntary agent and ſubiection being a morall act, it doth eſſentially depend on conſent: ſo that a man may by force and extremity be brought under the power of another, as unreaſonable creatures are, to be diſpoſed of, and trampled
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:155920:14"/>
on, whether they will or no: But a bond of ſubjection can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be put on him, nor a right to claime Obedience and Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice acquired, unleſſe a man become bound by ſome act of his owne Will. For, ſuppoſe another, from whom I am ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginally free, be ſtronger then I, and ſo bring mee under his mercy doe I therefore ſin if I doe not what he commands me? or can that act of violence paſſe into a morall title, without a morall principle?</p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>3</label> But this will be more manifeſt, if by induction I ſhew how other titles reſolve into this.<note place="margin">Monarchy by divine inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion.</note> I will begin with that of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine inſtitution. <hi>Saul</hi> and <hi>David</hi> were by the Sacrament of anointing deſigned to the Kingdome, as it were by Gods owne hand, which notwithſtanding, they were not actually Kings till the Peoples conſent eſtabliſhed them therein: That unction was a manifeſtation of the appointment of God, and when it was made knowne to the People, I thinke it had the power of Precept, to reſtraine the Peoples choice to that perſon; which if they had not done, they had reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted Gods ordinance. Yet they were not thereby actually endowed with Kingly power, but remained as private men, till the Peoples choice put them in actuall poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of that Power, which in <hi>David</hi> was not till after many yeares.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>4</label> Then for that of Uſuage or Preſcription; if any ſuch did ever conſtitute a Monarchie,<note place="margin">Monarchy by preſcription.</note> it was by vertue of an Univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall conſent by that Uſuage and Preſcription proved and implyed: For in a Popular ſtate, where one Man in the Communitie, by reaſon of great eſtate, Wiſdome, or other Perfection is in the eye of all the reſt, all reverence him, and his advice they follow: and the reſpect continues from the People to the houſe and family, for divers genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. In this caſe, ſubjection at firſt is arbitrary in the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; and if in time it become neceſſary, it is becauſe their Cuſtome is their Law; and its long continuance is equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valent to a formall Election: ſo that this Tenure and Right if it be good and more then at pleaſure, as it was at firſt, the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:155920:14"/>
conſiderate muſt needs aſcribe it to a conſent, and implicite choyce of the People.</p>
                  <p>But the mayn Queſtion is concerning Monarchy archie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>5</label> by Conqueſt;<note place="margin">Monarchy by conqueſt.</note> where at firſt ſight the Right ſeems gotten by the Sword, without the conſent and Choyce of the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, yea againſt it. Conqueſt is either 1. Totall where a full Conqueſt is made, by a totall ſubduing a people to the Will of the Victor: or 2. Partiall, where an entrance is made by the Sword: But the People either becauſe of the Right claymed by the Invader; or their unwillingneſſe to ſuffer the Miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of Warre, or their apparent inability to ſtand out in a way of Reſiſtance, or ſome other conſideration, ſubmit to a compoſition and contract of ſubjection to the Invader. In this latter it is evident, the Soveraignes Power is from the Peoples conſent; and the Government is ſuch as the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract and fundamentall agreement makes it to be if it be the firſt Agreement, and the pretender hath no former Title which remaines in force, for then this latter is invalid, if it include not and amount to a relinquiſhing and diſanulling of the Old. But the difficulty is concerning a full and meere Conqueſt; and of this I will ſpeak my mind clearly. Such a Warre and Invaſion of a People, which ends in a Conqueſt, 1. it is either upon the pretence or claim of a Title of Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raignty over the People invaded: and then, if the pretender prevaile, it is properly no Conqueſt, but the vindication of a Title by force of Armes. And the Government is not Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginall, but ſuch as the Title is by which he claymes it. 2. Or it is by One who hath no challenge of Right deſcending to him to juſtifie his claim and Invaſion of a People: Then if he ſubdue, he may properly be ſaid to come to his Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment by Conqueſt.</p>
                  <p>And there be who wholly condemne this title of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt as unlawfull,<note place="margin">Whether con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt give a iuſt title?</note> and take it for nothing elſe but a Natio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall and publike robbery: ſo one of the Anſwerers to Doctor <hi>Ferne,</hi> ſaies in his p. 10. <hi>Conqueſt may give ſuch a right as Plun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derers uſe to take in houſes they can maſter.— It is inhumane
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:155920:15"/>
to talke of right of Conqueſt in a Civill, in a Chriſtian State.</hi> But I cannot allow of ſo indefinite a Cenſure: rather I think the right of Conqueſt is ſuch as the precedent Warre was: if that were lawfull, ſo is the Conqueſt: For a Prince may be inva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, or ſo farre injured by a neighbour People, or they may be ſet on ſuch a pernicious enmitie againſt him and his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, that the ſafety of himſelfe and people may compell to ſuch a Warre, which warre if it end in Conqueſt, who can judge ſuch Title unlawfull? Suppoſe then Conqueſt may be a lawfull way of acquiſition: yet an immediate cauſe of right of Soveraignty; that is, of a Civill power of Government to which obedience is due, it cannot be: I ſay, an immediate cauſe, for a remote impulſive cauſe it oft is, but not an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediate formall cauſe; for that muſt ever be the conſent of the people, whereby they accept of, and reſigne up them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to a Government, and then their Perſons are morally bound, and not before. Thus far the force of conqueſt may goe; it may give a man title over, and power to poſſeſſe and diſpoſe of the Countrey and Goods of the Conquered; yea, the Bodies and lives of the Conquered are at the Will and Pleaſure of the Conquerour: But it ſtill is at the Peoples choice to come into a morall condition of ſubiection or not. When they are thus at the mercy of the Victor, if to ſave life they conſent to a condition of ſervitude or ſubiection, then that conſent, oath, or covenant, which they in that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremity make, being in <hi>relicita,</hi> bindes them, and they owe morall Duty. But if they would rather ſuffer the utmoſt violence of the Conquerour, and will conſent to no termes of ſubjection as <hi>Numantia</hi> in <hi>Spaine,</hi> and many other People have reſolved; they die or remaine a free People. Be they captived or poſſeſſed at pleaſure, they owe no duty, neither doe they ſin in not obeying; nor doe they reſiſt Gods ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, if at any time of advantage they uſe force to free themſelves from ſuch a violent poſſeſſion: yea perhaps, if before by contract they were bound to another, they ſhould ſin if to avoid death or bondage they ſhould ſweare or cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant fealty to a Conquerour, and it were more noble and laudable to die in the ſervice, and for the faith to their natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:155920:15"/>
Soveraigne. Thus I am perſwaded it will appeare an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>controlable truth in Policie, that the conſent of the People, either by themſelves or their Anceſtors is the only mean in ordinary providence by which ſoveraignty is conferred on a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Perſon or Family: neither can Gods ordinance be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veyed and People engaged in conſcience by any other means.</p>
                  <p>It hath been affirmed by ſome, that mixture and limitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>6</label> is inconſiſtent to ſucceſſive Monarchy;<note place="margin">Whether a Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narch by ſuc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceſsion may not be limited?</note> as if where ever Soveraignty is entailed to a ſucceſſion, it muſt needs be ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute: But I muſt profeſſe I cannot ſee how it can ſtand with truth: Rather I thinke, that both Elective and Heredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary Monarchy are indifferently capable of abſoluteneſſe or limitation. If a free, and not pre-ingaged People to any Government, by publike compact yeeld up themſelves to a Perſon, to be commanded by his Will as their ſupreme Law, during his naturall life, and no longer, can it be denied but that he is an abſolute, and yet Elective Monarch? unleſſe you will ſay, he is not abſolute, becauſe he cannot by his Will, as by a Law, bind them to elect his ſonne to ſucceed him, and change their Government into hereditary. But his being limited in this Clauſe doth not diſparage his So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraignty, or make his power of Government limited, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe this belongs not to preſent Government, but is a meere proviſion for the future. Againe, if the power of Ruling according to a Law, be by conſent conveyed to one Perſon, and his heires to ſucceed after him, how this ſhould come to be abſolute and the entailement ſhould overthrow the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution, I cannot imagine: If the whole latitude of power may be by a People made hereditary ſure a proportion may as well; unleſſe the limitation be ſuch as includes a repug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nancy to be perpetuall. Indeed this enſtating of a ſucceſſion makes that power irrevocable, during the continuance of that ſucceſſion but it makes it neither greater nor leſſe in the Succeſſor then was in his Progenitors, from whom hee derives it.</p>
                  <p>In a ſucceſſive Monarchy the Succeſſor holds by the ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginall <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>7</label>
                     <pb n="24" facs="tcp:155920:16"/>
Right of him who is the root of ſucceſſion; and is <hi>de jure</hi> King the immediate inſtant after his Predeceſſors de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſe: Alſo the people are bound <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> him, though they ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver take any Oath to his perſon. For as he commands in vertue of the originall Right, ſo they are bound to obey by vertue of the originall Covenant, and nationall Contract of Subiection: the new oath taken either by King or People, is but a reviving of the old; that the Conſcience of it by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newing might be the more freſh and vigorous: it neither gives any new power, nor addes or detracts from the old, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe by common agreement an alteration be made; and ſo the foundation in that clauſe is new, which cannot be with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the conſent of both parties.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. IIII.</hi> Of the Diviſion of Monarchy into Simple and Mixed.</head>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>1</label> THe third diviſion is into Simple and Mixed. Simple is when the Government abſolute or limited is ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truſted in the hands of one,<note place="margin">Simple and mixed Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy, what?</note> that all the reſt is by depu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation from him: ſo that there is no authority in the whole Body but his, or derived from him: And that One is either individually one Perſon, and then it is a ſimple Monarchy: Or one aſſociate Body, choſen either out of the Nobility, whence the Government is called a ſimple Ariſtocraty: or out of the Community, without reſpect of birth or ſtate, which is termed a ſimple Democracy. The ſupreme autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity reſiding excluſively in one of theſe three, denominates the Government ſimple, which ever it be.</p>
                  <p>Now experience teaching People, that ſeverall inconveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences are in each of theſe, which is avoided by the other: as aptneſſe to Tyranny in ſimple Monarchy: aptneſſe to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructive Factions in an Ariſtocracy: and aptneſſe to Confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion and Tumult in a Democracy. As on the contrary, each
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:155920:16"/>
of them hath ſome good which the others want, <hi>viz.</hi> Unity and ſtrength in a Monarchy; Counſell and Wiſedome in an Ariſtocracy; Liberty and reſpect of Common good in a Democracy. Hence the wiſedome of men deeply ſeene in State matters guided them to frame a mixture of all three, uniting them into one Forme, that ſo the good of all might be enjoyed, and the evill of them avoyded. And this mixture is either equall, when the higheſt command in a State by the firſt Conſtitution of it is equally ſeated in all three; and then (if firme Union can be in a mixture of Equality) it can be called by the name of neither of them but by the generall ſtile of a <hi>Mixed State:</hi> or if there be priority of Order in one of the three, (as I thinke there muſt be or elſe there can be no Unity) it may take the name of that which hath the precedency. But the firmer Union is, where one of the three is predominant and in that regard gives the denomination to the whole: So we call it a <hi>Mixed Monarchy,</hi> where the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity of ſhare in the ſupreme power is in one.</p>
                  <p>Now I conceive to the conſtituting of Mixed Monarchy <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>2</label> (and ſo proportionately it may be ſaid of the other.<note place="margin">What it is which conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes a mixed Monarchy?</note>)</p>
                  <p n="1">1. The Soveraigne power muſt be originally in all three, <hi>viz.</hi> If the compoſition be of all three ſo that one muſt not hold his power from the other, but all equally from the fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damentall <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Poſ. </seg>1</label> Conſtitution: for if the power of one be origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall, and the other Derivative, it is no mixture, for ſuch a Derivation of power to others is in the moſt ſimple Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy: Againe, the end of mixture could not be obteyned; for why is this mixture framed, but that they might confine each other from exorbitance, which cannot be done by a derivate power, it being unnaturall that a derived power ſhould turne back, and ſet bounds to its owne beginning.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. A full equality muſt not be in the three eſtates, though <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Poſ. </seg>2</label> they are all ſharers in the Supreame power; for if it were ſo, it could not have any ground in it to denominate it a Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchie, more then an Ariſtocracie or Democracie.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. A power then muſt be ſought wherewith the Monarch <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Poſ. </seg>3</label> muſt be inveſted, which is not ſo great as to deſtroy the
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:155920:17"/>
mixture; nor ſo titular as to deſtroy the Monarchy; which I conceive maybe in theſe particulars.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. If he be the head and Fountaine of the power which governs and executes the eſtabliſhed Lawes, ſo that both the other States as well <hi>conjunctim</hi> as <hi>diviſim,</hi> be his ſworne ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, and owe obedience to his commands, which are accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to eſtabliſhed Lawes.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. If he hath a ſole or chiefe power in capacitating and putting thoſe perſons or ſocieties in ſuch States and conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, as whereunto ſuch Supreme power by the foundations of the Government doth belong, and is annexed: ſo that though the Ariſtocratical and Democraticall power which is conjoyned to his, be not from him: yet the definement and determination of it to ſuch perſons is from him, by a ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary conſecution.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. If the power of convocating or cauſing to be put in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſtence, and diſſolving ſuch a Court or Meeting of the two other eſtates as is authoritative, be in him.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. If his authority be the laſt and greateſt, though not the ſole, which muſt eſtabliſh and adde a <hi>conſummatum</hi> to every Act. I ſay theſe, or any of theſe put into one perſon makes that State Monarchicall, becauſe the other, though they depend not on him <hi>quoad eſſentiam et actus formales,</hi> but on the prime conſtitution of the Government, yet <hi>quoad exiſtenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am et determinationem ad ſubjecta,</hi> they doe.</p>
                  <p>The Supreme power being either the <hi>Legiſlative</hi> or the <hi>Gubernative.</hi> In a mixed Monarchy ſometimes the mixture is the ſeate of the <hi>Legiſlative</hi> power, which is the chiefe of the two: The power of conſtituting officers for governing by thoſe Lawes being left to the Monarch: Or elſe the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macie of both theſe powers is jointly in all three: For if the Legiſlative be in one, then the Monarchy is not mixed but ſimple, for that is the Superiour, if that be in one, all elſe muſt needs be ſo too: By Legiſlative, I meane the power of making new Lawes, if any new be needfull to be added to the foundation: and the Authentick power of interpreting the old; For I take it, this is a branch of the Legiſlative and is as great, and in effect the ſame power.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="27" facs="tcp:155920:17"/>Every mixed Monarchy is limited: but it is not neceſſary <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>3</label> that every limited ſhould be mixed: For the Prince in a mixed Monarchy, were there no definement of him to a Law but onely this: that his Legiſlative acts have no validity without the allowance and joint authority of the other: this is enough to denominate it exactly a limited Monarchy: and ſo much it muſt have, if it be mixed. On the other ſide, if in the foundations of his Government he be reſtrained to to any Law beſides his own Will, he is a limited Monarch, though that both the Legiſlative and Gubernative pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er (provided he exceed not thoſe Lawes) be left in his owne hands: But then the Government is not mixed.</p>
                  <p>Now concerning the extent of the Princes power, and the <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>4</label> ſubjects duty in a mixed Monarchy,<note place="margin">How far the Princes power extends in a mixed Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy?</note> almoſt the ſame is to be ſaid, which was before in a limited: for it is a generall rule in this matter: ſuch as the Conſtitution of Government is, ſuch is the Ordinance of God: ſuch as the Ordinance is, ſuch muſt our duty of ſubjection be. No Power can chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge an obedience beyond its owne meaſure; for if it might, we ſhould deſtroy all Rules and differences of Government, and make all abſolute and at pleaſure. In every mixed Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipality.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, Looke what Power is ſolely entruſted and commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Aſſert. </seg>1</label> to the Prince by the fundamentall Conſtitution of the State, in the due execution thereof all owe full ſubjection to him, even the other Eſtates, being but ſocieties of his ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects bound to him by Oath of Allegeance as to their liege Lord.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, thoſe acts belonging to the power which is ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Aſſert. </seg>2</label> in a mixed Principle if either part of that Principle, or two of the three undertake to doe them it is invalid it is no binding Act; for in this caſe all three have a free Negative voice: and take away the priviledge of a Negative Voice, ſo that in caſe of refuſall the reſt have power to doe it without the third, then you deſtroy that. Third, and make him but a Looker on: So that in every mixed Government, I take it, there muſt be a neceſſity of concurrence of all three Eſtates
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:155920:18"/>
in the production of Acts belonging to that power, which is committed in common to them: Elſe ſuppoſe thoſe Acts valid which are done by any <hi>major</hi> part, that is, any two of the three, then you put it in the power of any two, by a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federacy at pleaſure to diſanull the third, or ſuſpend all its Acts, and make it a bare Cypher in Government.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Aſſert. </seg>3</label> Thirdly in ſuch a compoſed State, it the Monarch in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vade the power of the other two, or run in any courſe tend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the diſſolving of the conſtituted frame, they ought to employ their power in this caſe to preſerve the State from ruine; yea that is the very end and fundamentall aime in conſtituting all mixed Policies: not that they by croſſing and jarring ſhould hinder the publike good; but that, if one exorbitate, the power of reſtraint and providing for the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like ſafety ſhould be in the reſt: and the power is put into di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers hands, that one ſhould counterpoize and keep even the other: ſo that for ſuch other Eſtates, it is not onely lawfull to deny obedience and ſubmiſſion to illegall proceedings, as private men may, but it is their duty, and by the foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the Government they are bound to prevent diſſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the eſtabliſhed Frame.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Aſſert. </seg>4</label> Fourthly, the Perſon of the Monarch, even in theſe mixed Formes, (as I ſaid before in the limited) ought to be above the reach of violence in his utmoſt exorbitances: For when a People have ſworne allegeance, and inveſted a Perſon or Line with Supremacy, they have made it ſacred, and no ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſe can deveſt him of that power, irrevocably communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. And while he hath power in a mixed Monarchy, he is the Univerſall Soveraigne, even of the other limiting States: ſo that being above them, he is <hi>de jure</hi> exempt from any pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall hand.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Aſſert. </seg>5</label> Fifthly, that one inconvenience muſt neceſſarily be in all mixed Governments, which I ſhewed to be in limited Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernments, there can be no Conſtituted, Legall, Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tative Judge of the fundamentall Controverſies ariſing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the three Eſtates. If ſuch doe ariſe, it is the fatall diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe of theſe Governments, for which no ſalve can be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed; For the eſtabliſhed being of ſuch authority, would
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:155920:18"/>
                     <hi>ipſo facto</hi> overthrow the Frame, and turne it into abſolute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: So that if one of theſe, or two, ſay their power is inva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, and the Government aſſaulted by the other, the Accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed denying it, it doth become a controverſie: of this queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on there is no legall Judge, it is a caſe beyond the poſſible proviſion of ſuch a Government. The Accuſing ſide muſt make it evident to every mans Conſcience. In this caſe, which is beyond the Government, the Appeale muſt be to the Community, as if there were no Government; and as by Evidence mens Conſciences are convinced, they are bound to give their utmoſt aſſiſtance. For the intention of the Frame in ſuch States, juſtifies the exerciſe of any power, conducing to the ſafety of the Univerſality and Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment eſtabliſhed.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="part">
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:155920:19"/>
               <head>PART II. Of this particular MONARCHY.</head>
               <div n="1" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. I.</hi> Whether the Power wherewith our Kings are inve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted, be an Abſolute, or Limited and Moderated Power?</head>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>1</label>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Aving thus far proceeded in generall, before we can bring home this to a ſtating of the great controverſie, which now our ſins, Gods diſpleaſure, and evill turbulent men have rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed up in our lately moſt flouriſhing but now moſt unhappy Kingdome. Wee muſt firſt looke into the Frame and Compoſure of our Monarchy; for till we fully are reſolved of that, we cannot apply the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer generall Truths, nor on them ground the Reſolution of this ruining contention.</p>
                  <p>Concerning the Eſſentiall Compoſure of this Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that it is Monarchicall, is by none to be queſtioned: but the enquiry muſt be about the Frame of it. And ſo there are ſeven great queſtions to be proſecuted.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Queſt. <hi>1.</hi> ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</note>Firſt, <hi>whether it be a Limited Monarchy, or Abſolute?</hi> Here the queſtion is not concerning Power in the Exerciſe, but the Root and being of it: for none will deny but that
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:155920:19"/>
the way of Government uſed, and to be uſed in this Realme, is a deſigned way: Onely ſome ſpeake as if this Definement were an act of Grace from the Monarchs themſelves, being pleaſed at the ſuit, and for the good of the People, to let their power run into act through ſuch a courſe and current of Law: whereas, if they at any time ſhall thinke fit on great cauſes to vary from that way, and uſe the full extent of their power, none ought to contradict, or refuſe to obey. Neither is it the queſtion, Whether they ſin againſt God if they ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſe their power, and run out into acts of injury at pleaſure, and violate thoſe Lawes which they have by Publike Faith and Oath promiſed to obſerve; for none will deny this to be true, even in the moſt abſolute Monarch in the world. But the point controverted is punctually this, <hi>Whether the Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity which is inherent in our Kings be boundleſſe and abſolute, or li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mited and determined, ſo that the acts which they doe, or command to be done without that compaſſe and bounds, be not onely ſinfull in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, but invalid and non-authoritative to others?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Now for the determining hereof, I conceive and am in <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>2</label> my Judgement perſwaded,<note place="margin">Aſſert.</note> 
                     <hi>that the Soveraignty of our Kings is radically and fundamentally limited,</hi> and not onely in the Uſe and Exerciſe of it: And am perſwaded ſo on theſe grounds and Reaſons.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, Becauſe the Kings Majeſty himſelfe, who beſt <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>1</label> knowes by his Councell the nature of his own power, ſayes, that<note n="a" place="margin">Declar from Newmarket Mart. <hi>9. 1641</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>the Law is the meaſure of his power:</hi> which is as full a conceſſion of the thing as words can expreſſe. If it be the meaſure of it, then his power is limited by it; for the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure is the limits and bounds of the thing limited. And in his Anſwer to both the Houſes concerning the <hi>Militia,</hi> ſpeaking of the men named to him, ſayes, <hi>If more power ſhall be thought fit to be granted to them, then by Law is in the Crowne it ſelfe, His Maieſty holds it reaſonable, that the ſame be by ſome Law firſt veſted in him, with power to transferre it to the theſe perſons, &amp;c.</hi> In which paſſage it is granted that the Powers of the Crown are by Law, and that the King hath no more then are veſted in him by Law.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="32" facs="tcp:155920:20"/>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>2</label> Secondly, becauſe it is in the very Conſtitution of it mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xed, as I ſhall afterwards make it appeare, then it is radically limited; for as I ſhewed before, every mixed Monarchy is li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mited, though not on the contrary: for the neceſſary con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexion of other power to it, is one of the greateſt limitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. A ſubordination of Cauſes doth not ever prove the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme Cauſe of limited virtue; a co-ordination doth al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>3</label> Thirdly, I prove it from the ancient, ordinary, and recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved denominations; for the Kings Majeſty is called out <hi>Liege,</hi> that is, <hi>Legall Soveraigne;</hi> and we his <hi>Liege</hi> that is, his <hi>Legall Subjects:</hi> what doe theſe names argue, but that his So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraignty and our ſubjection is legall that is, reſtrained by Law?</p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>4</label> Fourthly, had we no other proofe, yet that of <hi>Preſcription</hi> were ſufficient: In all ages, beyond record, the Lawes and Cuſtomes of the Kingdome have been the Rule of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; Liberties have been ſtood upon, and Grants thereof, with limitations of Royall power, made and acknowledged by <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> and other publike and ſolemne acts; and no Obedience acknowledged to be due but that which is accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to Law, nor claimed but under ſome pretext and title of Law.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>5</label> Fifthly, the very Being of our Common and Statute Lawes, and our Kings acknowledging themſelves bound to governe by them, doth prove and preſcribe them Limited: for thoſe Lawes are not of their ſole compoſing, nor were they eſtabliſhed by their ſole Authority, but by the concur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of the other two Eſtates: ſo that to be confined to that which is not meerly their owne, is to be in a limited condition.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Pleaders for defenſive armes Sect. <hi>2.</hi> &amp; <hi>4.</hi>
                     </note>Some there be which have lately written on this ſubject, who take another way to prove our Government limited by Law, <hi>viz.</hi> by denying all abſolute Government to be law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full; affirming that Abſolute Monarchy is not at all Gods Ordinance, and ſo no lawfull power ſecured from reſiſtance. What is their ground for this? God allowes no man to rule as he liſt, nor puts mens lives in the pleaſure of the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narch:
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:155920:20"/>
It is a power arbitrary and injurious. But I deſire thoſe Authors to conſider, that in abſolute Monarchy there is not a reſignation of men to any Will or liſt, but to the <hi>rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable Will of the Monarch,</hi> which having the Law of reaſon to direct it, is kept from injurious acts. But ſee for defence of this Government, <hi>Part</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 2.</p>
                  <p>Having ſet downe thoſe Reaſons on which my Judgement <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>3</label> is ſetled on this ſide, I will conſider the maine Reaſons wherby ſome have endeavoured to prove this Government to be of an abſolute nature, and will ſhew their invalidity. Many Divines perhaps inconſiderately, perhaps wittingly for ſelf ends, have beene of late yeares ſtrong Pleaders for <hi>Abſoluteneſſe</hi> of Monarchicall Power in this Land; and preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Obedience on the Conſciences of People in the utmoſt extremity, which can be due in the moſt abſolute Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy in the world; but I ſeldome or never heard or read them make any difference of Powers, but uſually bring their proofes from thoſe Scriptures, where ſubjection is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to the <hi>higher Powers,</hi> and all reſiſtence of them for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden and from Examples taken out of the manner of the government of <hi>Iſrael</hi> and <hi>Judah:</hi> as if any were ſo impious to contradict thoſe truths, and they were not as well obeyed in Limited Government as in Abſolute; or as if Examples taken out of one Government do alwayes hold in another, unleſſe their aime were to deny all diſtinction of Governments, and to hold all abſolute, who have any where the ſupreme power conveyed to them.</p>
                  <p>Among theſe, I wonder moſt at that late diſcourſe of Dr. <hi>Ferne,</hi> who in my Judgement avoucheth things inconſiſtent, and evidently contradictory one to the other: For in his Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face he acknowledges our Obedience to be limited and cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſcribed by the Lawes of the Land, and accordingly to be yeelded or denied to the higher Power; and that <hi>he is as much againſt an abſolute Power in the King and to raiſe him to an arbitrary way of Government, as againſt reſiſtence on the Subjests part:</hi> alſo, <hi>that his power is limited by Law, Sect.</hi> 5. Yet on the other ſide he affirmes, <hi>That the King holds his Crown by conqueſt;</hi>
                     <pb n="34" facs="tcp:155920:21"/>
that it is <hi>deſcended to him by three Conqueſts, Sect.</hi> 2. that we e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven our Senate of Parliament hath not ſo much plea for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtence as the ancient <hi>Romane</hi> Senate had under the <hi>Romane</hi> Emperours, whoſe power we know was abſolute, <hi>Sect,</hi> 2. that in Monarchy the judgement of many is reduced ro one: that Monarchy ſettles the chief power and finall Judgment in one, <hi>Sect.</hi> 5 what is this but to confeſſe him limited: and yet to maintain him abſolute?</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Arguments on the contrary diſſolved.</note>But let us come to the Arguments. Firſt, ſay they, our Kings came to their right by Conqueſt; yea, ſaies the Dr. by three Conqueſts: He meanes the <hi>Saxons, Danes,</hi> and <hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans,</hi> as appears afterwards: Therefore their right is abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute. Here, that they may advance themſelves, they care not though it be on the ruine of publique liberty, by bringing a whole Nation into the condition of conquered ſlaves: But to the Argument. 1. Suppoſe the Antecedent true, the Conſequution is not alwaies true; for as is evident before in the firſt Part. All Conqueſt doth not put the Conqueror in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to an abſolute right. He may come to a right by Conqueſt: but not ſole Conqueſt; but a partiall, occaſioning a Right by finall Agreement; and then the right is ſpecificated by that fundamentall agreement: Alſo he may by ſword proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute a claime of another nature: and in his war intend on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly an acquiring of that claimed right, and after conqueſt reſt in that: Yea farther, he may win a Kingdome meerly by the Sword and enter on it by right of Conqueſt: yet conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that right of conqueſt hath too much of force in it to be ſafe and permanent; he may thinke conqueſt the beſt meane of getting a Kingdome, but not of holding, and in wiſdome for himſelfe and poſterity, gaine the affections of the people by deſerting that Title, and taking a new by Politique agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or deſcend from that right by fundamentall grants of liberties to the people, and limitations to his own power: but theſe things I ſaid in effect before, in the firſt part, only here I have recalled them, to ſhew what a <hi>non ſequitur</hi> there is in the Argument. But that which I chiefly intend, is to ſhew the infirmity or falſehood of the Antecedent: it is an Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſertion moſt untrue in it ſelfe; and pernitious to the State:
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:155920:21"/>
Our Princes profeſſe no other way of comming to the Crown, but by right of ſucceſsion to rule free ſubjects in a legall Monarchy. All the little ſhew of proofe theſe Aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors have, is from the root of ſucceſsion: So <hi>William</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly called the Conquerour. For that of the <hi>Saxons</hi> was an expulſion not a Conqueſt, for as our Hiſtories record, They comming into the Kingdome drove out the Britaines, and by degrees planted themſelves under their Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders; and no doubt continued the freedome they had in <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many:</hi> unles we ſhould thinke that by conquering they loſt their own Liberties to the Kings for whom they conquered and expelled the Britiſh into <hi>Wales.</hi> Rather I conceive, the Originall of the ſubjects libertie was by thoſe our fore-fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers brought out of <hi>Germany:</hi> Where, as <hi>Tacitus reports,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Tacit. de Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rib. German. Sect. <hi>3.</hi> &amp; <hi>5.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>nec Regibus infinita aut libera poteſtas:</hi> Their Kings had no abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute but limited power: and all weighty matters were diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patched by generall meetings of all the Eſtates. Who ſees not here the antiquity of our Liberties and frame of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment? ſo they were governed in <hi>Germany,</hi> and ſo here to this day, for by tranſplanting themſelves, they changed their ſoyl; not their manners and Government: Then, that of the <hi>Danes</hi> was indeed a violent Conqueſt; and, as all violent rules, it laſted not long; when the Engliſh expelled them they recovered their Countrey and Liberties together. Thus it is clear, the Engliſh Libertie remained to them till the <hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> Invaſion, notwithſtanding that Daniſh interruption. Now for Duke <hi>William,</hi> I know nothing they have in him but the bare ſtile of Conqueror, which ſeems to make for them: The very truth is, and everie intelligent reader of the Hiſtorie of thoſe times will atteſt it, that Duke <hi>William</hi> pretended the grant and gift of King <hi>Edward</hi> who died with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out children and he came with forces into this Kingdome, not to Conquer but make good his Title againſt his enemies: his end of entring the Land was not to gaine a new abſolute Title but to vindicate the old limited one, whereby the Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh <hi>Saxon</hi> Kings his Predeceſſors held this Kingdome. Though his Title was not ſo good as it ſhould be,<note place="margin">Camb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>n. Britan. Norma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> yet it was better then <hi>Harolds,</hi> who was onely the Sonne of <hi>Goodwyn,</hi>
                     <pb n="36" facs="tcp:155920:22"/>
Steward of King <hi>Edwards</hi> houſe; Whereas <hi>William</hi> was Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen to <hi>Emma</hi> mother to the ſaid King <hi>Edward;</hi> by whom he was adopted; and by ſolemne promiſe of King <hi>Edward</hi> was to ſucceed him: Of which promiſe <hi>Harold</hi> himſelfe became ſurety, and bound by oath to ſee it performed: Here was a faire Title, eſpecially <hi>Edgar Atheling</hi> the right Heire being of tender age, and diſ-affected by the people. Neither did he proceed to a full Conqueſt, but after <hi>Harola</hi> who uſurped the Crown was ſlain in battle, and none to ſucceed him, the Throne being void, the people choſe rather to ſubmit to <hi>William</hi> and his Title, then endure the hazzard of ruining war, by oppoſing him, to ſet up a new King: It is not to be imagined, that ſuch a Realme as <hi>England</hi> could be conquered by ſo few, in ſuch a ſpace, if the peoples voluntary accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance of him and his claime had not facilitated and ſhortned his undertaking. Thus we have it related in Mr. <hi>Cambd<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>n,</hi> that before <hi>Harold</hi> uſurped the Crown, moſt men thought it the wiſeſt Policie to ſet the Crown on <hi>Williams</hi> head, that by performing the Oath and promiſe, a Warre might be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented: And that <hi>Harold</hi> by aſſuming the Crown, provo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked the whole Clergy and Eccleſiaſticall State againſt him: and we know how potent in thoſe daies the Clergy were in State affaires: Alſo that after one battle fought wherein <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rold</hi> was ſlain, he went to <hi>London,</hi> was received by the Londo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, and ſolemnly inaugurated King as unto whom by his own ſaying the Kingdome was by Gods Providence appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and by vertue of a gift from his Lord and Couſen King <hi>Edward,</hi> the glorious, granted: ſo that after that battell the remainder of the war was diſpatched by Engliſh forces and Leaders But ſuppoſe he did come in a Conqueror, yet he did not eſtabliſh the Kingdome on thoſe termes, but on the old Lawes, which he reteyned and authorized for himſelfe and his Succeſſors to governe by. Indeed after his ſettlement in the Kingdome, ſome <hi>Norman</hi> Cuſtomes he brought in, and to gratify his ſouldiers diſpoſſeſſed many Engliſh of their eſtates, dealing in it too much like a Conqueror: but the tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all by twelve men, and other fundamentalls of Government, wherein the Engliſh freedome conſiſts, he left untouched,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:155920:22"/>
which have remained till this day: On the ſame Title he claimed and was inaugurated, was he King which was a title of rightfull ſucceſsion to <hi>Edward:</hi> therfore he was indeed King not as Conqueror, but as <hi>Edwards</hi> Succeſſor, and on the ſame right as he and his Predeceſſors held the Crowne. As alſo by the grant of the former Lawes and forme of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, he did equivalently put himſelfe and ſucceſſors into the State of legall Monarchs, and in that Tenure have all the Kings of this Land held the Crown till this day, when theſe men would rake up and put a Title of Conqueſt upon them, which never was claimed or made uſe of by him who is the firſt root of their ſucceſsion.</p>
                  <p>Another reaſon which they produce is the ſucceſsive na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>4</label> of this Monarchy: for with them, to be elective and limited, and to be ſucceſsive and abſolute, are equipollent: They conceive it impoſsible that a Government ſhould be Hereditary and not abſolute: But I have enough made it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear, <hi>Part</hi> 1. <hi>Chap.</hi> 2. <hi>Sect.</hi> 6. That ſucceſsion doth not prove a Monarchie abſolute from limitation, though it proves it abſolution from interruption and diſcontinuance, during the being of that ſucceſsion to which it is defined. And that which they object that our Kings are actually ſo before they take the Oath of governing by Law, and ſo they would be, did they never take that Oath; wherefore it is no Limitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of their royall power, is there alſo anſwered in the next <hi>Sect.</hi> and that ſo fully, that no more need be ſaid. The ſame Law which gives the King his Crown immediatly upon the deceaſe of his Predeceſſor, conveyes it to him with the ſame Determinations and Prerogatives annexed, with which his Progeintors enjoyed it ſo that he entring on that Origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall Right, his ſubjects are bound to yeild obedience, before they take any Oath: And he is bound to the Lawes of the Monarchy before he actually renewes the bond by any Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonall Oath. There is yet another argument uſually brought to this purpoſe, taken from the Oath of Allegiance: but of that I ſhall have occaſion to ſpeake hereafter.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="chapter">
                  <pb n="38" facs="tcp:155920:23"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. II.</hi> Suppoſing it be in the Platforme limited.<note place="margin">Queſt. 2.</note> Wherein, and how far forth it is limited and defined?</head>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Poſ. </seg>1</label> I Conceive it fundamentally limited in five particulars. Firſt, in the whole latitude of the <hi>Nomotheticall</hi> power; ſo that their power extends not to eſtabliſh any Act, which hath the Being and ſtate of a Law of the Land: nor give an authenticke ſenſe to any Law of doubtfull and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverted meaning, ſolely and by themſelves, but together with the concurrent Authority of the two other Eſtates in Parliament.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Poſ. </seg>2</label> Secondly, in the Governing Power, there is a confinement to the Fundamentall Common Lawes, and to the ſuperſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive Statute Lawes, by the former concurrence of Powers enacted, as to the Rule of all their Acts and Executions.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Poſ. </seg>3</label> Thirdly, in the power of conſtituting Officers, and meanes of governing; not in the choice of Perſons for that is intruſted to his Judgement, for ought I know, but in the conſtitution of Courts of Judicature: For as hee cannot Judge by himſelfe or Officers, but in Courts of Juſtice; ſo thoſe Cours of Juſtice muſt have a conſtitution by a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currence of the three Eſtates: They muſt have the ſame power to conſtitute them, as the Lawes which are diſpenſed in them.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Poſ. </seg>4</label> Fourthly, in the very ſucceſſion; for though ſucceſſion hath been brought as a <hi>Medium</hi> to prove the Abſoluteneſſe of this Government yet if it be more throughly conſidered, it is rather a proofe of the contrary; and every one who is a ſucceſſive Monarch is ſo far limited in his power that he cannot leave it to whom he pleaſes, but to whom the Fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damentall Law concerning that Succeſſion hath deſigned it. And herein though our Monarchy be not ſo far limited as that of <hi>France</hi> is ſaid to be, where the King cannot leave it to
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:155920:23"/>
his Daughter, but to his Heire male, yet reſtrained it is; ſo that ſhould he affect another more, or judge another fitter to ſucceed, yet he cannot pleaſe himſelfe in this, but is limi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the next Heire borne, not adopted or denominated: which was the caſe 'twixt Queene <hi>Mary</hi> and the Lady <hi>Jane.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Laſtly, in point of Revenue wherein their Power extend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Poſ. </seg>5</label> not to their Subjects Eſtates; by Taxes and Impoſitions to make their owne what they pleaſe, as hath been acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged by <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> and lately by the <hi>Petition of Right,</hi> the caſe of <hi>Ship-money, Conduct-money, &amp;c.</hi> Nor, as I conceive, to make an Alienation of any Lands, or other Revenues an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexed by Law to the Crowne. I meddle not with perſonall limitations, whereby Kings, as well as private men, may li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit themſelves by Promiſe and Covenant, which being par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular, bind onely themſelves; but of thoſe which are radi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call, and have continued during the whole current of ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion from unknowne times. Other limitations, it is likely, may be produced by thoſe who are skilfull in the Lawes: but I beleeve they will be ſuch as are reducible to ſome of theſe, which I take to be the principall and moſt apparent limitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of this Monarchy, and are a moſt convincing induction to prove my Aſſertion in the former Chapter, <hi>That this Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy, in the very Mold and Frame of it, is of limited conſtitution.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. III.</hi> Whether it be of a Simple or Mixed Conſtitution?<note place="margin">Queſt. 3.</note>
                  </head>
                  <p>WHen the Government is ſimple, when mixed; al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>1</label> where the mixture muſt be, which denomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nates a mixed Government, is explained <hi>Part</hi> 1. <hi>Cap.</hi> 3. Now I conceive it a cleare and undoubted Truth, that the Authority of this Land is of a compounded and mixed nature in the very root and conſtitution thereof. And my judgment is eſtabliſhed on theſe grounds.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="40" facs="tcp:155920:24"/>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>1</label> Firſt, It is acknowledged to be a Monarchy mixed with Ariſtocracy in the houſe of Peeres,<note place="margin">Anſwer to the <hi>19.</hi> Propoſit.</note> and Democracy in the houſe of Commons. Now (as before was made appeare in the firſt Part) it is no mixture which is not in the Root and Supremacy of Power: for though it have a ſubordination of inferiour Officers, and though the Powers inferiour be ſeat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in a mixed ſubject, yet that makes it not a mixed Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; for it is compatible to the ſimpleſt in the world, to have ſubordinate mixtures.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>2</label> Secondly, that Monarchy where the legiſlative power is in all three, is in the very Root and Eſſence of it compoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded and mixed of thoſe three; for that is the height of power, to which the other parts are ſubſequent and ſubſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vient: ſo that where this reſideth in a mixed ſubject that is in three diſtinct concurrent Eſtates, the conſent and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe of all moſt free, and none depending on the will of the other, that Monarchy is in the moſt proper ſenſe and in the very modell of it of a mixed conſtitution: but ſuch is the ſtate of this Monarchy, as appeares in the former que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, and is ſelf-apparent.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>3</label> Thirdly, that Monarchy, in which three Eſtates are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted, to the end that the power of one ſhould moderate and reſtrain from exceſſe the power of the other, is mixed in the root and eſſence of it: but ſuch is this, as is confeſſed in the anſwere to the ſaid Propoſitions. The truth of the <hi>ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jor</hi> will appeare, if we conſider how many wayes proviſion may be made in a Politicall Frame to remedy and reſtraine the exceſſes of Monarchy. I can imagine but three wayes. Firſt, by conſtituting a legall power above it, that it may be regulated thereby, as by an over-ruling power: Thus wee muſt not conceive of our two houſes of Parliament, as if they could remedy the exorbitances of the Prince by an Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority ſuperiour to his; for this were to ſubordinate him to the two Houſes, to ſet a ſuperiour above the Soveraigne, that is, to deſtroy the being of his Monarchicall power. Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, by an originall conveyance to him of a limited and legall power ſo that beyond it he can doe no poteſtative act; yet conſtituting no formall legall power to refraine or redreſſe
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:155920:24"/>
his poſſible exorbitances; here is limitation without mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of another conſtituted power: As the former of theſe overthrowes the power of the Soveraigne, ſo this makes no proviſion for the iudemnity of the people. Thirdly, now the never enough to be admired wiſedome of the Architects and Contrivers of the frame of Government in this Realme (who ever they were) have found a third way, by which they have conſerved the Soveraignty of the Prince; and alſo made an excellent proviſion for the Peoples free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, by conſtituting two Eſtates of men, who are for their condition Subjects, and yet have that intereſt in the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that they can both moderate and redreſſe the exceſſes and illegalities of the Royall power, which (I ſay) cannot be done, but by a mixture, that is, by putting into their hands a power to meddle in acts of the higheſt function of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; a power not depending on his will, but radically their owne, and ſo ſufficient to moderate the Soveraignes power.</p>
                  <p>Now what can reaſonably be ſaid in oppoſition to theſe <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>2</label> grounds, proving a fundamentall mixture, I cannot deviſe. Neither indeed is a mixture in the Government denied by the greateſt Patrons of irreſiſtibility; onely ſuch a mixture they would faine make it, which might have no power of poſitive reſiſtence. I will therefore ſet down what they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bably may or do object to this purpoſe, and will ſhew the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>validity thereof.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, this mixture ſeems not to be of diſtinct powers but of <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>1</label> a Power &amp; a Councell; authority in the Prince to give pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to Acts, and counſell in the two Houſes to adviſe and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe wholeſom Acts; as if the royall power alone did give life to the Law: onely he is defined in this power, that he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not animate any Act to the being of a Law, but ſuch as is propoſed unto him by this great and Legiſlative Councell of Parliament. <hi>Sol,</hi> This were probable, ſuppoſing the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment were onely in the nature of a Counſell; but we know it is alſo a Court, the <hi>High Court of Parliament:</hi> Now it is evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent that a Court is the ſeat and ſubject of Authority and
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:155920:25"/>
power, and not barely of counſell and advice.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>2</label> Secondly, the two Houſes together with the King, are the ſupreme Court of the Kingdome; but taken diviſely from the King, it is no Court, and conſequently hath no power. <hi>Sol.</hi> Suppoſe them no entire Court divided from the King, yet they are two Eſtates of the three which make up the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme Court; ſo that they have a power and authority, though not complete and ſufficing to perfect an Act, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the concourſe of the third: For it appeares by the Acts of that Court, that every of the three Eſtates hath a Legiſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive power in it; every Act being enacted by the Kings moſt excellent Majeſty, and by the <hi>Authority of the Lords and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons aſſembled in Parliament.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>3</label> Thirdly, they have an authority, but in ſubordination to <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>3</label> the King, and derived from him, as his Parliament. Indeed this is a maine Queſtion, and hath very weighty Arguments on both ſides,<note place="margin">Whether the authority of the two Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes be derived from the King?</note> 
                     <hi>viz. Whether the authority of both the Houſes be a ſubordinate authority, and derived from the King as its originall?</hi> Three Reaſons ſeeme ſtrong for the affirmative: Firſt, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is his Parliament, ſo called and acknowledged: If his Court, then the power whereby they are a Court is his power, derived from him, as the power of other Courts is. Secondly, becauſe he hath the power of calling and diſſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving it. Thirdly, becauſe he is acknowledged in the Oaths of Allegeance and Supremacy to be the Head, and of ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme authority in the Kingdome, and all ſubject to him.</p>
                  <p>And whereas ſome make anſwere that he is <hi>Singulis major,</hi> but <hi>Vniverſis minor,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Treatiſe enti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tituled,</hi> A ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler Anſwer to Dr. <hi>Ferne.</hi>
                     </note> ſo the Anſwerer to Doctor <hi>Ferne,</hi> I won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der that the Propoſition of the Obſervator, that the King is <hi>Vniverſis minor,</hi> ſhould be ſo much exploded. Every mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber <hi>ſcorſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> is a ſubject, but all <hi>collection</hi> in their houſes are not: And hee ſayes ſimply, the Houſes are co-ordinate to the King, nor ſubordinate; that the Lords ſtile, <hi>Comites,</hi> or <hi>Peeres,</hi> implies in Parliament a co-ordinative ſociety with his Majeſty in the Government. I conceive this Anſwerer to avoid one extreme falls on another; for this is a very overthrow of all Monarchy, and to reduce all Government
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:155920:25"/>
to Democracy; For looke where the <hi>apex poteſtatis</hi> is, there is the Government. Alſo it is againſt Common Reaſon: For the King, is he not King of the Kingdome? and what is the Kingdome but all united? all the particulars knit toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in one body politick? ſo that if he be King of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, he is <hi>Vniverſis major</hi> too; for the King is <hi>major,</hi> and the Kingdome is the united univerſe of the People. Thus thoſe expreſſions are ſome of them falſe, ſome though <hi>ſecundum quid</hi> true; yet ſpoken ſimply, and in that manner, are ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalous and incompatible to Monarchy. Thus you ſee what may be ſaid on the one ſide, to prove the King to be the ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginall of all power, even of that which is in the Houſes of Parliament aſſembled.</p>
                  <p>On the other ſide are as weighty Arguments to prove the contrary, <hi>viz.</hi> That the two Houſes authority is not depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, nor derived from the Royall power. Firſt, the autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of the Houſes being Legiſlative, is the ſupreme, and ſo cannot bee derived. Three concurrent Powers producing one ſupreme act, as con-cauſe, joint cauſes of the ſame high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt effect cannot have a ſubordination among themſelves in reſpect of that caſualty; it not being imaginable how a pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er can cauſe the ſupreme effect, and yet be a ſubordinate and derived power. Secondly, the end of conſtituting theſe two Eſtates being the limiting and preventing the exceſſes of the third, their power muſt not be totally dependent and deri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved from the third, for then it were unſuitable for the end for which it was ordained: For to limit an Agent by a pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er ſubordinate and depending on himſelf, is all one as to leave him at large without any limitation at all. Thirdly, that which hath beene ſpoken of a mixed Monarchy, doth fully prove that the two other powers which concurre with the Monarch, to conſtitute the mixture, muſt not be altogether ſubordinate to it, and derived from it. I muſt profeſſe theſe Reaſons to prevaile with me, that I cannot conceive how the authority of the two Houſes can in the whole being of it, be a dependent and derived power.</p>
                  <p>That we may find out the truth amidſt this potent con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiction <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>4</label>
                     <pb n="44" facs="tcp:155920:26"/>
of both ſides,<note place="margin">Reſolution of the Queſtion.</note> recourſe muſt be had to the Architecture of this Government, whereof I muſt declare my ſelf to be ſo great an Admirer, that what ever more then humane wiſedom had the contriving of it, whether done at once, or by degrees found out and perfected, I conceive it un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paralleld for exactneſſe of true policy in the whole world; ſuch a care for the Soveraignty of the Monarch, ſuch a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion for the liberty of the People, and that one may bee juſtly allayed, and yet conſiſt without impeachment of the other, that I wonder how our Forefathers in thoſe rude un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poliſhed times could attain ſuch an accurate compoſure. Firſt then ſuppoſe a people, either compelled to it by conqueſt, or agreeing to it by free conſent, Nobles and Commons ſet over themſelves by publike compact one Soveraigne, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigne up themſelves to him and his heires, to be governed by ſuch and ſuch Fundamentall Lawes: there's a ſupremacy of power ſet up, though limited to one courſe of exerciſe. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, then becauſe in all Governments after caſes will come, it requiring an addition of Lawes, ſuppoſe them cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanting with their Soveraigne, that if cauſe be to conſtitute any other Lawes, hee ſhall not by his ſole power doe that worke, but they reſerve at firſt, or afterwards it is granted them (which is all one) a hand of concurrence therein, that they will be bound by no Lawes, but what they joyne with him in the making of. Thirdly, becauſe though the Nobles may perſonally convene, yet the Commons (being ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny) cannot well come together by themſelves to the doing of ſuch a worke, it be alſo agreed, that every Corporation of the Commons ſhall have power to depute one or more to be for the whole in this publike legiſlative buſineſſe; that ſo the Nobles by themſelves, the Commons by their Depu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties aſſembling, there may be repreſentatively the whole bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, having Commiſſion to execute that reſerved authority for eſtabliſhing new Lawes. Fourthly, becauſe the occaſion and need of making new Lawes, and authentick expounding the old, would not be conſtant and perpetuall, and it would carry an appearance of a Government in which were three Heads and chiefe Powers, they did not ſtabliſh theſe Eſtates
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:155920:26"/>
to be conſtantly exiſtent, but occaſionally, as the cauſes for which they were ordained ſhould emerge and happen to be. Fifthly, becauſe a Monarchy was intended and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore a Supremacy of power (as farre as poſſible) muſt be reſerved for one, it was concluded that theſe two Eſtates ſhould be Aſſemblies of his Subjects ſworne to him, and all former Lawes; the new, which by agreement of Powers ſhould be enacted, were to be his Lawes, and they bound to obey him in them as ſoone as eſtabliſhed: And being ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed that he who was to governe by the Lawes, and for the furtherance of whoſe Government the new Lawes were to be made, ſhould beſt underſtand when there was need, and the aſſembling and diſſolving the two Eſtates meeting, was a power of great priviledge, it was put into the Princes hand by writ to convocate and bring to exiſtence, and to adjourne and diſmiſſe ſuch meetings Sixthly, in proceſſe of time Princes not caring much to have their Government looked into, or to have any power in act but their own, took advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage of this power of convocating thoſe Eſtates, and did more ſeldome then need required make uſe of it; whereon proviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on was made, and a time ſet within which an Aſſembly of Parliament was to be had. Now when you have made theſe ſuppoſitions in your minde, you have the very modell and platforme of this Monarchy, and we ſhall eaſily find what to anſwer to the arguments before produced on either ſide. For firſt it is his Parliament, becauſe an aſſembly of his ſubjects, convocated by his Writ, to be his Councell, to aſſiſt him in making Lawes for him to govern by: yet not his, as other Courts are altogether deriving their whole authority from the fulneſſe which is in him. Alſo his power of aſſembling and diſſolving proves him thus far above them, becauſe in their exiſtence they depend on him; but their power and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority <hi>quoad ſpecificationem,</hi> the being and kind of it, is from originall conſtitution: for they expect no Commiſſion and authority from him, more then for their meeting and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducing into exiſtence; but exiſting, they worke according to the priviledges of their conſtitution, their acts proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from their conjunct authority with the Kings, not from
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:155920:27"/>
its ſubordination to the Kings. The oath of Allegeance binds them, and reſpects them as his ſubjects, to obey him, govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing according to eſtabliſhed Lawes: it ſuppoſes and is built upon the foundations of this Government, and muſt not be interpreted to overthrow them<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> he is thereby acknowledged to be ſupreme ſo far as to rule them by Lawes already made; not ſo far as to make Lawes without them, ſo that it is no derogation to their power; and I beleeve of theſe things none can make any queſtion. Therein conſiſts the accurate Judgement of the Contrivers of this Forme, they have given ſo much into the hands of the ſoveraign, as to make him tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a Monarch; and they have reſerved ſo much in the hands of the two Eſtates, as to enable them to preſerve their owne liberty.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. IIII.</hi> 
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>4</label> How farre forth it is mixed; and what parts of the Power are referred to a mixed Principle?</head>
                  <p>I Shall be the briefer in this, becauſe an anſwer to it may be eaſily collected out of the precedent Queſtions: for he who knowes how farre this Government is limited, will ſoon diſcerne how farre it is mixed, for the Limitation is moſtly affected by the mixture:<note place="margin">Three points of mixture.</note> but diſtinctly, I conceive that there are three parts of the power referred to the joint concourſe of all three Eſtates: So that either of them not conſenting or ſuſpending its influence the reſt cannot reduce that power ordinarily and legally into act.</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> The firſt is the Nomotheticall power, underſtanding by it the power of making, and authentick expounding Lawes, ſo that I believe an act cannot have the nature and forme of a Law of the Land, if it proceed from any one, or two of theſe, without the poſitive concurrence of the third.</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, The power of impoſing taxes and payments on mens eſtates: that the King by himſelf cannot aſſume mens
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:155920:27"/>
properties by requiring impoſitions not granted him by Law, is often confeſted: And that the other Eſtates cannot doe it by themſelves, I conceive it as unqueſtionable: For it were ſtrange to give that to the ſecondary and aſsiſting Powers, which is denied to the Soveraigne and principall. If it be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected that every Corporation electing Deputies, and autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rizing them to be <hi>vice totius Communitatis,</hi> do thereby grant them power, and entruſt them as to make laws to bind them, ſo to diſpoſe of any part of their eſtate, either by rate or payment for the publique good: I anſwer, that they are by that deputation enabled as for one, ſo for the other; that is, according to the fundamentall uſuage of the Kingdome; that is, by the joint conſent of the other eſtates, for though the houſe of Commons is choſen by the people, and they repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent the people, yet the repreſentation doth not give them a power which was not in the people. Now the people have no power to doe an act which either directly, or by conſequence doth put it in the will and pleaſure of any one or two of the Eſtates, to overthrow the other: But this power of open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and ſhutting the Purſe of the Kingdome is ſuch a power, that if it be in one or two of the Eſtates, without the third, then they by that power might neceſſitate that other to doe any act, or diſable it from its owne defence. This and the Legiſlative power have ſuch a neerneſſe, that they cannot be divided, but muſt be in the ſame ſubject: this is ſo great a power, that put it abſolutely in any Eſtate ſingle, you make that Eſtate in effect abſolute, making the reſt dependent and beholding to it for their ſubſiſtence.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, the power of diſpatching the affaires of the <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Kingdome which are of greateſt difficulty and weight, the <hi>ardua regni,</hi> which the Writ for convocating the other Eſtates doth mention, ſuppoſing thereby that ſuch difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties are not to be diſpatched by the power of one alone; for if they were, why then are the two other convocated to be aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting? I acknowledge many matters of great moment may be done by the Regall power, and in ſuch caſe it may be ſaid, that the other Eſtates are gathered <hi>ad molius tra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſigendum,</hi> that the adviſe and ſenſe of the Community may be for dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:155920:28"/>
But I conceive there be two ſorts of affaires, which ought not to be tranſacted without the concurrence of all three. Firſt, ſuch as concerne the publike ſafety and weale, ſo far as ſtable detriment or advantage comes to the whole body by the well or ill carriage thereof; for then there is the ſame reaſon as in making new Lawes: For why was not the power of making any new Lawes left in the hands of one, but reſerved for the concurrence of all three? ſave becauſe the end of the Architects was, that no new thing which was of ſo much concernment as the ſtable good and dammage of the Kingdome, ſhould be introduced without the conſent and advice of the whole: ſo that if any buſineſſe be of that moment, that it is equipollent to a Law in the publike in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt, it ſhould be managed by ſuch an authority and way as that is. Secondly, ſuch as introduce a neceſſity of publike charge, be it matter of War or elſe, if to the effecting of it the Purſe of the Kingdome be required, it is evident that it ought to be done by the concurrence of all, becauſe they onely jointly (as appeares before) have power to impoſe a publike charge on the eſtates of men. And it were all one to put the power of our eſtates in the hands of one, as to put the power of ſuch undertakings in his ſole hands, which of neceſſity bring after them an engagement of publike ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. V.</hi> 
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>5</label> How far forth the two Estates may oppoſe and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt the will of the Monarch?</head>
                  <p>THis Queſtion is in the generall already handled in the <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>1</label> firſt Part, ſo that it will be eaſie to draw thoſe An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers there to this particular here: Therefore con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formably to what I then affirmed, I will anſwere this Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion by divers Poſitions.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Poſ. </seg>1</label> Firſt, the Monarch working according to his power, not
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:155920:28"/>
exceeding the Authority which God and the Lawes have conferred on him, is no way to be oppoſed either by any or all his Subjects, but in conſcience to Gods ordinance obeyed. This is granted on all ſides.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, if the will and command of the Monarch ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Poſ. </seg>2</label> the limits of the Law, it ought for the avoidance of ſcandall and offence be ſubmitted to, ſo it be not contrary to Gods Law, nor bring with it ſuch an evill to our ſelves, or the publike, that we cannot be acceſſary to it by obeying. This alſo will find no oppoſition. Diſobedience in light ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, in which we are not bound, makes an appearance of ſlighting the power, and is a diſreſpect to the perſon of the Magiſtrate. Therefore Chriſt, to avoyd ſuch offenſe, would pay tribute, though he tells <hi>Peter,</hi> He was free, and need not have done it.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, if hee command a thing which the Law gives <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Poſ. </seg>3</label> him no authority to command, and it be ſuch as would bee inconvenient to obey, in this caſe obedience may lawfully be denied: This alſo findes allowance from them which ſtand moſt for royall power. Doctor <hi>Ferne</hi> in his Preface acknowledges obedience to be limited and circumſcribed by the eſtabliſhed Lawes of the Land, and accordingly to bee yeelded or denied. And <hi>Sect.</hi> 1. ſayes he, <hi>We may and ought to deny obedience to ſuch commands of the Prince as are unlawfull by the Law of God, yea by the establiſhed Laws of the land.</hi> Here he ſayes more then we ſay; yea more then ſhould be ſaid, as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peares in the ſecond Poſition: it is not univerſally true, that we ought.</p>
                  <p>Fourthly, if he exceed the limits of the Law, and proceed <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Poſ. </seg>4</label> in courſes illegall, meanes there are which it is agreed upon the Subjects may uſe to reduce him to legall Government; ſo much Doctor <hi>Ferne</hi> allowes <hi>Sect.</hi> 4. Cries to God, Petition to the Prince, Deniall of Obedience, Deniall of Subſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>Fifthly but the point in controverſie is about poſitive and <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Poſ. </seg>5</label> forcible reſiſtance, the lawfulneſſe of which ſome doe utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deny and others doe as confidently maintaine: but yet this point might be brought to a narrower ſtate then in
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:155920:29"/>
the confuſed handling of it, it uſually is: by diſtinguiſhing twix't forceable reſiſtence uſed againſt the Kings own perſon, or againſt inferiour Officers and Inſtruments adviſing to, or executing the illegall commands.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>2</label> For the firſt, as I have before expreſſed my ſelfe, force ought not to be uſed againſt the perſon of the Soveraigne, on any pretence whatever, by any or all his ſubjects; even in limited and mixed Monarchies: for if they be truly Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchs, they are irrevocably inveſted with Soveraignty, which ſets their perſons above all lawfull power and force. Alſo the Soveraign power being ſo conferred on that perſon: The perſon and power cannot be really ſundred, but the force which is uſed to the one, muſt alſo violate the other: for power is not in the Soveraigne as it is in inferiour Officers: as water is otherwiſe in the ſpring then in the channells, and pipes deriving it: It is not inſeperably in them, and therfore they offending, force may be uſed againſt them without vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of the Ordinance of Authority. Theſe Arguments approve it unlawfull in any: That which the Dr. brings, I approve as ſtrong againſt all private force, where he allowes defence againſt the perſon of the Prince himſelfe, ſo farre as to ward his blowes, but not to returne blowes, no though for naturall defence: becauſe the Common-Wealth is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned in his perſon, <hi>Sect.</hi> 2. And to divert a private evill by inducing a publique, is unjuſt and unlawfull: ſo that for this point of force againſt the perſon of the Prince: I thinke there ought to be no contention. If any have bin ſo raſh to hold it lawfull on theſe grounds, that the whole Kingdome is above him becauſe they make him King, and that by miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carriage he may make a forfeiture, and ſo lay himſelfe open to force: I do iudge theſe grounds very inſufficient: unles the Kingdome reſerve a ſuperiority to it ſelf, or there be a fundamentall clauſe of forfeiture on ſpecified cauſes; and then it is not properly a Monarchy: but all this hath been already handled in the generall Part.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, for Inſtruments of oppreſsion of publique li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty if the wrong be deſtructive, and no other meanes of
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:155920:29"/>
prevention, but force, be left: I am perſwaded it may be u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and poſitive reſiſtence made againſt them; And if I find any contradiction from the moſt rigid Patrones of Royalty, it muſt be only in this point. And here I muſt complaine of the indiſtinct dealing of that Doctor in this matter; who mingleth both theſe points together: and ſcarce ſpeakes any thing to reſolve mens conſciences in this: But ſpeakes either in generall, or elſe of force againſt the Princes owne perſon: Whereas I thinke, the caſe which ſticks moſt on the conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence at this time, is this latter: Of oppoſing, mi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>-leading and miſ-imployed ſubjects, which he ſpeaks very little to. Nay, he ſeems to me, after all his diſclaiming of reſiſtence, to come home to us, and though ſparingly, yet to aſſent to lawfullnes of reſiſtence in this point. For <hi>Sect.</hi> 2. ſpeaking of <hi>Davids</hi> guard of armed men: He ſaies, It was to ſecure his perſon againſt the cut-throats of <hi>Saul,</hi> if ſent to take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way his life: He meanes to ſecure it by force, for Souldiers are for force: He meanes no negative ſecuring by flight, for that may be done even againſt <hi>Saul</hi> himſelfe: but he ſpeaks of ſuch a ſecuring which might only be againſt cut-throats. So then he grants ſecuring by force againſt theſe: But they went on <hi>Sauls</hi> command, and moſtly with his preſence. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, in the inſtance of <hi>Eliſha,</hi> he ſeemes to acknowledge lawfullneſſe of perſonall defence againſt the ſudden and il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legall aſſaults of Meſſengers, he means by force, for he ſpeaks of ſuch which he will not allow in publique, which can be underſtood of none, but by force: But it appears the Doct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>or in his whole diſcourſe hath avoided this point of reſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of miſ-imployed ſubjects; which yet is the alone point which would have given ſatisfaction: for before it appeares, we agree in all the reſt, and in this too for ought I know, he having not diſtinctly ſaid any thing againſt it.</p>
                  <p>Now concerning this caſe of forceable reſiſtence of infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>3</label> perſons miſ-imployed to ſerve the illegall deſtructive commands of the Prince, I will doe two things. 1.<note place="margin">Whether re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtence of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments of will be law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full?</note> I will maintaine my <hi>Aſſertion</hi> by convincing Arguments. 2. I will ſhew the invalidity of what is ſaid againſt it.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="52" facs="tcp:155920:30"/>
                     <note place="margin">Aſſert. 1.</note>This then is my <hi>Aſſertion:</hi> The two Eſtates in Parliament may lawfully by force of Armes reſiſt any perſons or num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of perſons adviſing or aſsiſting the King in the perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of a command illegall and deſtructive to themſelves, or the publique.</p>
                  <p n="1">
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Arg. </seg>1</label> 1. Becauſe that force is lawfull to be uſed for the publique conſervation which is no reſiſtence of the Ordinance of God; for that is the reaſon condemning the reſiſtence of the Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers: Now this is no reſiſtence of Gods Ordinance: For by it neither the perſon of the Soveraigne is reſiſted, nor his power: Not his perſon, for we ſpeak of Agents imployed, not of his own perſon: Nor his power; For the meaſure of that, in our Government, is acknowledged to be the Law: And therefore he cannot confer Authority to any beyond Law: ſo that thoſe Agents deriving no Authority from him: are meere Inſtruments of his Will: Unauthorized perſons; in their aſſaults Robbers, and, as Dr. <hi>Ferne</hi> calls them, Cut-throats. If the caſe be put, What if the Soveraigne himſelfe in perſon be preſent with ſuch Aſſaylants, joining his perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall aſsiſtence in the execution of his Commands? It is much to be lamented, that the will of the Prince ſhould be ſo im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuous in any ſubverting Act, as to hazzard his own perſon in the proſecution of it. Yet ſuppoſing ſuch a caſe, all coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cells and courſes muſt betaken, that no violence be offered to his perſon, and Profeſsion of none intended: But no reaſon the preſence of his perſon ſhould priviledge ruining Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments from ſuppreſsion, and give them an immunity to ſpoil and deſtroy ſubjects, better themſelves; His perſon being ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured from wrong; His power cannot be violated in ſuch an Act, in which none of it can be conferred on the Agents. And ſure <hi>David,</hi> though he avoided laying hands or uſing any vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence againſt the perſon of <hi>Saul,</hi> and on no extremity would have done it: Yet for the Cut-throats about him, if no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther means would have ſecured him, he would have reſcued himſelfe by force from their outrage: Though <hi>Saul</hi> was in their company: Elſe what intended he by all that force of Souldiers: And his enquiry of God at <hi>Keilah:</hi> by which it is plain, He had an intent to have kept the place by force, if
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:155920:30"/>
the people would have ſtuck to him: Neither is it to the purpoſe which the Dr. ſaies, <hi>Sect.</hi> 2. That his example was extraordinary, becauſe he was anointed and deſigned to ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed <hi>Saul,</hi> for that being but a deſignation, did not exempt him from the duty of ſubjection for the preſent, or leſſen it, as is plain by the great conſcience he made of not touching <hi>Saul:</hi> But he knew it was one thing to violate <hi>Sauls</hi> Perſon and Power, and another to reſiſt thoſe Inſtruments of Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny, the Cut-throats which were about him.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, Becauſe without ſuch power of reſiſtence in <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Arg. </seg>2</label> the hands of ſubjects, all diſtinction and limitation of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment is vain: and all formes reſolve into abſolute and arbitrary; for that is ſo, which is unlimited; and that is unlimited, not onely which hath no limits ſet: but alſo which hath no ſufficient Limits, for to be reſtrained from doing what I will, by a power which can reſtrain me no lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger nor otherwiſe then I will, is all one, as if I were left at my own Will. I take this to be cleare: Now it is as cleare, that without this forceable reſiſtence of Inſtruments of uſurped power be lawfull, no ſufficient limits can be to the Princes Will and all Lawes bounding him are to no purpoſe. This appeares by enumerating the other meanes, Prayer to God: Petition to the Prince: Deniall of obedience: Deniall of Subſidie: a moderate uſe of the power of denying as Doctor <hi>Ferne</hi> calls it: Theſe are all: but what are theſe to hinder, if a Prince be minded to overthrow all, and bring the whole Government to his own Will? For Prayer, and Petition, theſe are put in to fill up the number: They are no limitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, they may be uſed in the moſt abſolute Monarchy; for deniall of obedience, that may keep me from being an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument of publique ſervitude; but Princes Wills never want them which will yeild obedience, if I deny it; Yea e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to deſtroy all the reſt, if nothing be left them but to ſuffer: Then for deniall of Subſidie, if he may by thouſands of Inſtruments take all, or what he, or they pleaſe, and I muſt not reſiſt: what need he care whether the people deny or grant: If a Prince be taught, that he may do it: caſes and reaſons will ſoon be brought to perſwade him, that in them
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:155920:31"/>
he may lawfully doe it; as late experiences have given us too much Teſtimonie: Thus it is apparent, that the deniall of this Power of Reſiſtence of Inſtruments overthrowes and makes invalid all Government, but that which is abſolute: and reduces the whole world <hi>de jure</hi> to an abſolute ſubjecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that is, ſervitude: for the end of all conſtitution of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derated forms is not that the ſupreme power might not law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully exorbitate, but that it might have no power to exor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitate.</p>
                  <p>The Dr. is conſcious hereof; and therefore tells us in his <hi>Sect.</hi> 5. This is the very reaſon which is made for the Popes power of curbing and depoſing Kings in caſe of hereſie: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe elſe the Church, ſaies the <hi>Papiſt,</hi> hath no meanes for the maintenance of the Catholique Faith, and its own ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty: But who ſees not the vaſt difference 'twixt theſe two? and that the ſame reaſon may be concluding here, which is apparently <hi>non</hi> concluding there; For 1. They thereby would draw to the <hi>Pope</hi> an authoritative power: we no ſuch ſuperiour power: but only a power of reſiſtence for ſelf-con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation which nature and the Law of reaſon gives to every one; and may ſtand with the condition of ſubjection and inferiority. 2. They on this reaſon give the <hi>Pope</hi> a Power o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the very perſon of the King; we only of reſiſting of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>authorized invading deſtroyers, comming under the colour of an authority which is not in the Soveraigne to be derived. 3. They prove a civill right for ſpirituall reaſons, we onely for civill reaſons. 4. The Church and the faith are conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuted in their very formall being from Chriſt himſelfe, who is the head and great Shepheard immediately in his owne perſon: and as it is his owne family; ſo he keeps the power of preſerving it in his owne hands; having made direct and particular promiſes to aſſure us of their upholding againſt all ſubvertion, by his own power: ſo that here is aſſurance e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, without viſible meanes of force for a ſpirituall body, which lives by faith. But in a civill State there is no ſuch aſſurance nor ſupporting promiſes: power onely in the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>defined being of it, being Gods immediate Ordinance, and not in this ſpecificated or determinate being: wherefore it
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:155920:31"/>
hath no ſuch immediate proviſion made for its preſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, no promiſe of a divine power for its ſtanding: but as it is left by God to mens wiſdome to contrive the frame, ſo to their providence to eſtabliſh meanes of preſervation. As the body is outward and Civill, ſo the upholding meanes muſt be ſuch; ſpirituall and infallibly aſſuring a Formed State hath not, as the Church and Faith have; if there be none of outward force and power neither, then none at all it hath, and is in ill caſe indeed. But there is an art full of venome, when a truth can not bee beaten downe by juſt reaſoning, then to make it odious by hatefull compariſons: ſo in this caſe aſperſions are caſt, as if the Patrons of Reſiſtence did borrow the Popiſh and Jeſuiticall grounds, and their Poſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons as dangerous to Kings, as the Jeſuites hell-bred and blou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy Principles: whereas it appeares by all this diſcourſe, and I am perſwaded is written in Capitall Letters in the very Conſcience of them which deſpitefully object it, that there is no congruity at all 'twixt their Doctrines, no more then 'twixt Light and Darkneſſe.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, becauſe ſuch power is due to a publike State for <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Arg. </seg>3</label> its preſervation, as is due to a particular perſon: But every particular perſon may lawfully by force reſiſt illegall deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive Miniſters, though ſent by the command of a legall So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraigne, provided no other meanes of ſelfe-preſervation be enough. This Aſſumption the Doctor ſeemes to grant; he denies it to be lawfull againſt the Perſon of the Prince, but in effect yeelds it againſt ſubordinate perſons: But the main is againſt the Propoſition, and the Doctor is ſo heavie a friend to the State that he thinkes it not fit to allow it that liberty he gives every private man. But whoſe Judgement will concurre with his herein, I cannot imagine; for ſure the Reaſon is greater, the publike ſafety being far more precious, and able to ſatisfie the dammages of a publike reſiſtence, then one particular mans is of a private. But of this more in an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to his Reaſons.</p>
                  <p>Fourthly, becauſe it is a power put into the two Eſtates by <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Arg. </seg>4</label> the very reaſon of their Inſtitution; and therefore they not onely may, but alſo ought to uſe it for publike ſafety: yea
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:155920:32"/>
they ſhould betray the very truſt repoſed in them by the Fundamentals of the Kingdome if they ſhould not. An au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority Legiſlative they have: Now to make Lawes and to preſerve Lawes are acts of the ſame power; yea, if three powers jointly have intereſt in making of Lawes, ſurely ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of theſe ſeverally have, and ought to uſe that power in preſerving them. Alſo that the authority which the Houſes have is as well given them for preſerving the government by eſtabliſhed lawes, as for eſtabliſhment of lawes to govern by, is a truth proved by the conſtant uſe of their power to that end, in correcting the exorbitance of inferiour Courts, queſtioning delinquent Judges and Officers of State for violations, and much is done in this kinde by the ſole authority of the Houſes, without the concurrence or expectance of Royall power: ſo then, ſuppoſing they have ſuch an authority for ſafety of publike Government, to queſtion and cenſure in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriour Officers for tranſgreſſions, though pretending the Kings authority, can it be denied but that their authority will beare them out to uſe forcible reſiſtence againſt ſuch, be <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Arg. </seg>5</label> they more or fewer.</p>
                  <p>Fifthly, the Kings Warrant under his hand exempts not a Malefactor from the cenſure of a Court of Juſtice, nor pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment impoſed by Law, but the Judge muſt proceed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him according to Law: for the Law is the Kings publike and authoritative Will; but a private Warrant to doe an unlawfull act, is his private and unauthoritative Will: wherefore the Judge ought to take no notice of ſuch War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, but to deale with the Offendor as no other then a pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate man. This proves that ſuch Inſtruments thus illegally warranted, are not authorized; and therefore their violence may be by force reſiſted, as the aſſaults of private men, by any; and then much rather by the Houſes of Parliament: which, ſuppoſing them divided from the King to have no complete authority, yet ſure they have two parts of the greateſt Legiſlative authority. But I feare I ſhall ſeeme ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfluous, in producing Arguments to prove ſo cleare a truth: Is it credible that any one will maintaine ſo abject an eſteeme of their authority, that it will not extend to reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtence
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:155920:32"/>
of private men, who ſhould endevour the ſubverſion of the whole frame of Government, on no other Warrant then the Kings Will and Pleaſure? Muſt they be meerly paſſive? Is patience, and the deniall of their Votes to a ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion, all the oppoſition they muſt uſe, if a King (which God forbid) ſhould on his Royall pleaſure ſend Cut-throats to deſtroy them as they ſit in their Houſes? Is all their au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority (if the King deſert them or worſe) no more then to Petition, and ſuffer; and by a moderate uſe of their power of denying, diſſent from being willing to be deſtroyed? If power of reſiſting by force of ſubverters armed by the Kings Will (for by his Authority they cannot) be unlawfull for them, all theſe abſurdities muſt follow: yea, the vileſt In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument of Oppreſſion, ſhewing but a Warrant from the King to beare him out, may range and rage all his dayes through a Kingdome, to waſte and ſpoile, taxe and diſtraine, and at utmoſt of his inſolence muſt have no more done to him by the Parliament it ſelfe, then to ſtay his hand, as the baſeſt Servant may his Maſters, or the meaneſt Subject the Kings owne hand; by the Doctors own confeſſion. Conſider then and admire, if any men of learning will deny this power of forcible reſiſtence of Miniſters, of ſubverting commands to be lawfull. I have thus far confirmed my aſſertion, not that I finde any openly oppoſing it, but becauſe the Doctor and ſome other ſeeme to have a mind that way, and doe ſtrike at it, though not profeſſedly and in open diſpute.</p>
                  <p>For the ſeverall proofes brought in behalfe of Reſiſtence, ſome of them prove as much as is here aſſerted; others are not to the purpoſe. Particularly, that of the Peoples reſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Jonathan</hi> from his Fathers bloudy reſolution proves law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe of hindering unreaſonable ſelf-deſtructive purpoſes, even in abſolute Monarchies, if it prove any thing. That of <hi>Vzzal's</hi> thruſting out by the Prieſts, is not to the purpoſe: but <hi>Davids</hi> raiſing and keeping Forces about him, and his purpoſe at <hi>Keilah,</hi> proves the point directly <hi>viz.</hi> Lawfulneſſe of forcible reſiſtance of Cut-throats, even though <hi>Saul</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe were in preſence: This the Doctor ſees plainly, and therefore ſhuffles it off, by ſaying, <hi>His example is extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary;</hi>
                     <pb n="58" facs="tcp:155920:33"/>
as if he were not a preſent Subject, becauſe he was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned by Gods revealed counſell to be a future King. And he confeſſes <hi>Eliſha's</hi> example of ſhutting the doore againſt the Kings meſſenger proves perſonall defenſe againſt ſudden il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legall aſſaults of meſſengers, which is the thing in Queſtion.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect </seg>4</label> Let us now view the ſtrength of what is ſaid againſt reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtence whether any thing comes home againſt this Aſſerti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.<note place="margin">Arguments on the contrary diſſolved.</note> The Doctors proofes from the old Teſtament come not to the matter: <hi>Moſes,</hi> and afterwards the Kings, were of Gods particular deſignation, ſetting them abſolutely over the people, on no condition or limitation; ſo that did they prove any thing, yet they concerne not us, reſpecting a Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of another nature. But particularly, that of <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rah</hi> and the Princes rebelling againſt <hi>Moſes,</hi> is not to the matter; it was a reſiſtence of <hi>Moſes</hi> owne Perſon and Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice; and doubtleſſe penury of other proofes cauſed this and the reſt here to be alledged: For that 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 8 18. how in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſequent is it, to ſay, the people ſhould cry unto the Lord, therefore they had no other meanes to helpe them but cries to God; though (I confeſſe) in that Monarchy they had not. That ſpeech 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 26 9. was moſt true there, and is as true here, but not to the purpoſe, being ſpoken of the Kings owne Perſon. But the maine authority brought againſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtence, is that <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. and on that Doctor <hi>Ferne</hi> builds his whole diſcourſe: Let us therefore ſomething more largely conſider what is deduced out of that Text. Firſt, he ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes the King to be the <hi>Supreme</hi> in Saint <hi>Peter,</hi> and the <hi>Higher power</hi> in Saint <hi>Paul.</hi> Secondly, hee collects <hi>All perſons,</hi> every ſoule is forbidden to reſiſt. Thirdly, that then was a ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding Senate, which not long before had the ſupreme Power in the Romane State: It is confeſſed; but that they could challenge more at that time when Saint <hi>Paul</hi> writ then our great Councell will or can, I deny: For that State devol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving into Monarchy by Conqueſt, they were brought under an Abſolute Monarchy, the Senate it ſelfe ſwearing full ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection to the Prince; his Edicts and Acts of Will were Lawes, and the Senates conſent onely <hi>pro forma,</hi> and at plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:155920:33"/>
required. He who reads <hi>Tacitus</hi> cannot but ſee the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate brought to a condition of baſeſt ſervitude, and all Lawes and Lives depending on the will of the Prince: I wonder then the Doctor ſhould make ſuch a parallel. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed the Senate had been far more then ever our Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments were or ought to be: but now that was far leſſe then our Parliament hath been, or (I hope) ever will be: They were become the ſworne Vaſſals of an abſolute Emperour, ours the ſworne Subjects of a Liege or Legall Prince. Fourthly, he ſayes, then was more cauſe of Reſiſtence, when Kings were Enemies to Religion, and had overthrown Lawes and Liberties. I anſwere, There were no cauſes for Reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtence: Not their enmity to Religion, had they but a legall power, becauſe Religion then was no part of the Laws and ſo its violation no ſubverſion of eſtabliſhed government. And for the overthrow of Lawes and Liberties, that was paſt and done, and the government new, the Senate and all the reſt actually ſworne to abſolute Principality: Now an Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of abſolute Monarchy was conſtituted, the ſacred bond of an Oath had made it inviolate. But what would he inferre hence, all being granted him? Sure this he doth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend, That every ſoule among us, ſeverall, and conjoyned in a Senate, muſt be ſubject for conſcience, muſt not reſiſt, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der paine of Damnation: All this, and what ever beſides he can juſtly infer out of that Text, we readily grant: But can any living man hence collect, that therefore no reſiſtence may be made to fellow-ſubjects, executing deſtructive ille<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gall acts of the Princes will in a legall Monarchy? Will he affirme that the Ordinance of God is reſiſted, and Damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion incurred thereby? Gods Ordinance is the Power, and the Perſon inveſted with that power; but here force is offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to neither as before I have made it appeare. And here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in we have B. <hi>Bilſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> conſenting, where he ſayes,<note place="margin">Bi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>n of ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>je<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> p <hi>94,</hi> &amp; <hi>280.</hi>
                     </note> that <hi>the ſupe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour power here forbidden to be reſisted, is not the Princes will againſt his Lawes but agreeing with his Lawes.</hi> I thinke the day it ſelfe is not more cleare then this ſatisfaction, to all that can bee concluded out of that Text: ſo the foundation of all that diſcourſe is taken from it, if his intent were thence to prove
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:155920:34"/>
unlawfulneſſe of Reſiſtence of Inſtruments of Arbitrarineſſe in this Kingdome.</p>
                  <p>Let us alſo conſider the force of his Reaſons, whether they impugne this point in hand. He ſayes, ſuch power of reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtence would be no fit meanes of ſafety to a State, but prove a remedy worſe then the diſeaſes. His Reaſons, firſt, becauſe it doth tend to the overthrow of that order, which is the life of a Common-wealth; it would open a way to People, upon the like pretences, to reſiſt, and even overthrow power duly adminiſtred. 2 It may proceed to a change of government. 3. It is accompanied with the evills of Civill-Warre. 4. On the ſame ground the two Houſes proceed againſt the King, may the people proceed to reſiſtence againſt them; accuſing them not to diſcharge their truſt. Laſtly, ſeeing ſome muſt be truſted in every State. It is reaſon the higheſt and finall truſt, ſhould be in the higheſt power. Theſe are his main reaſons on which he builds his concluſion againſt reſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence.</p>
                  <p>To his firſt, I ſay it were ſtrange if reſiſtence of diſtruct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ive diſorder ſhould tend to the overthrow of Order: It may for the time diſturbe, as Phyſick while it is in working di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturbes the naturall bodie, if the peccant humors make ſtrong oppoſition: but lure it tends to health, and ſo doth this reſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of diſorder to Order. Neither would it open a way for the people to violate the Powers; for doing right can open no way to the doing of wrong If any wicked ſeditious ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits ſhould make uſe of the Vail of Juſtice to cover unnatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Rebellion: Shall a peoples right and liberty be taken from them to prevent ſuch poſsible abuſe? Rather let the foulneſſe of ſuch pretences diſcover it ſelfe, ſo God and good men will abhorre them: ſuch Cloakes of Rebellion have in former ages been taken off, and the Authors brought to juſt confuſion, without the expence of the liberties of this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.</p>
                  <p>To the ſecond; muſt not Inſtruments be reſiſted, which actually intend, and ſeeked a chang of Government: becauſe ſuch reſiſtence may proceed to a chang of Government? Is not an unlikely poſsibility of change to be hazarded, rather
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:155920:34"/>
then a certaine one ſuffered? But I ſay, It cannot proceed to a chang of Government, unles it exceed the meaſure of law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full reſiſtence: yea it is impoſsible, that reſiſtence of Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments ſhould ever proceed to a change of Government; for that includeth the greateſt reſiſtence and violation of the perſon and power of the Monarch, the lawfullneſſe of which I utterly diſclaime.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, it is not ever accompanied with the evills of Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill Warre: But when the Princes Will findes enough Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of their Countreys ruine to raiſe it. And then the miſchife of that war muſt light on thoſe which raiſe it: But ſuppoſe it may enſue, yet a temporary evill of war is to be choſen rather then a perpetuall loſſe of liberty, and ſubver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the eſtabliſhed frame of a Government.</p>
                  <p>In the fourth, I deny the parity of reaſon: for the two Houſes are bodies conſtituted and endowed with legiſlative authority, and truſt of preſervation of the frame, by the Fundamentalls of the Kingdome: which the people out of thoſe Houſes are not. Againe the Government being com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed of a threefold conſenting power, one to reſtraine the exorbitance of another: All three together are abſolute and equivalent to the power of the moſt abſolute Monarch: The concurrent Will of all three, makes a Law, and ſo it is the Kingdomes Law.</p>
                  <p>To the laſt, I anſwer, In every State ſome muſt be truſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and the higheſt truſt is in him who hath the Supreame power: Theſe two the Supreame Truſt, and the Supreame Power are inſeperable: And ſuch as the power is, ſuch is the truſt: An abſolute power ſuppoſes an abſolute truſt: A Power allayed with the annexion of another power as here it is, ſuppoſeth a truſt of the ſame nature. A joynt truſt, yet ſaving the ſupremacie of the Monarch, ſo far forth as it may be ſaved,<note place="margin">How farre forth the ſword is in the hand of the Monarch?</note> and not be abſolute and the others authority nullified. It may be further argued: that it being the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogative Royall to have the managing of the ſword, that is, legall force, in the Kingdome; none can, on any pretence whatever uſe lawfull force, either againſt him, or any, but by his Will: for it is committed to him by law, and to none
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:155920:35"/>
but whom he aſsignes it to: ſo that the Lawes of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome putting all power of force and Armes into his truſt, have placed him, and all thoſe who ſerve him, in a ſtate of irreſiſtiblenes in reſpect of any lawfull force. This is a point much ſtood on and on this ground, the Parliament now aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuming the diſpoſing of the <hi>Militia</hi> by an Ordinance, it is complained on, as a uſurping of what the Law hath commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the King as his Prerogative; The oppoſing of which Ordinance by a Commiſsion of <hi>Array,</hi> was the beginning of this miſerable Civill-Warre. I will diſtinctly lay down my Anſwer hereto, ſubmitting it to every impartiall judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
                  <p n="1">
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Poſ. </seg>1</label> 1. The power of the Sword being for defence of the Lawes, by puniſhing violators, and protecting ſubjects, it is ſubſervient to Government, and muſt needs belong to him who is entruſted with the Government, as a neceſſarie requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite without which he cannot performe his truſt.</p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Poſ. </seg>2</label> 2. As it is an appendix to the power of Government, and goes along with it, ſo it goes under the ſame termes: belon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging to the Prince, as the other doth: <hi>ſc.</hi> abſolutely, to uſe at will, where the Monarchie is abſolute; or with limita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, to uſe according to Law, where the Monarchy is limi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted: ſo that, in this Government the Armes and ſword of the Kingdome is the Kings, to a defined uſe committed to him; <hi>viz</hi> For defence of the Lawes and Frame of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment eſtabliſhed, and not for arbitrary purpoſes, or to enable Miniſters to execute commands of meer Will.</p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Poſ. </seg>3</label> 3. The two Houſes in virtue of the Legiſlative authority, in part reſiding in them, are intereſted in the preſervation of Lawes and Government, as well as the King: And in caſe, the King ſhould miſimploy that power of Arms to ſtrength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en ſubverting Inſtruments: Or in caſe the Lawes and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment be in apparent danger, the King refuſing to uſe the ſword to that end of preſervation for which it was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to him: I ſay, in this caſe, the two Eſtates may by extraordinary and temporary Ordinance aſſume thoſe Armes, wherewith the King is entruſted, and performe the Kings truſt: And though ſuch Ordinance of theirs is not
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:155920:35"/>
formally legall, yet it is eminently legall, juſtified by the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry intent of the Architects of the Government, when for theſe uſes they committed the Armes to the King. And no doubt they may command the ſtrength of the Kingdome to ſave the being of the Kingdome: for none can reaſonably imagine the Architectonicall Powers, when they commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the power of government and Armes to one to preſerve the Frame they had compoſed, did thereby intend to diſable any, much leſſe the two Eſtates, from preſerving it, in caſe the King ſhould faile to doe it in this laſt need. And thus doing the Kings Worke, it ought to be interpreted as done by his Will: becauſe as the Law is his Will, ſo that the Law ſhould be preſerved is his Will, which he expreſſed when he undertooke the government: 'Tis his deliberate Will, and ought to be done, though at any time he oppoſe by an after-Will, for that is his ſudden Will, as Doctor <hi>Ferne</hi> himſelfe <hi>Sect.</hi> 1. doth teach us to diſtinguiſh.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. VI.</hi> In what caſes the other Estates may, without or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>6</label> the Kings Perſonall conſent, aſſume the Armes of the Kingdome?</head>
                  <p>WHo ever were the Authors of that Booke lately <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>1</label> publiſhed, ſtiled,<note place="margin">Whether it be lawfull to take up armes againſt the Magiſtrate, perverting his power to a wrong end?</note> 
                     <hi>Scripture and Reaſon pleaded for de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenſive Armes,</hi> have laid new and over-large grounds for reſiſtence. Two Aſſertions they endevour to maintaine: Firſt, <hi>thoſe Governours (whether ſupreme or others) who under pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of authority from Gods Ordinance, diſturb the quiet and peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able life in Godlineſſe and Honeſty, are farre from being Gods Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance in ſo doing,</hi> Sect. 3. Secondly, <hi>This Tyranny not being Gods Ordinance, they which reſiſt it even with Armes, reſiſt not the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of God.</hi> Hereon, <hi>Sect.</hi> 4. they free Chriſtians, even in the Apoſtles time, and ſo under the Romane Emperours, or any
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:155920:36"/>
other Government, from neceſſity of paſſive ſubjection in caſe of perſecution; affirming, that the Chriſtians in thoſe firſt Perſecutions, had they been ſtrong enough, might have uſed Armes for defence againſt the Tyranny of their Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours. Their ground is from the Reaſons uſed by the Apoſtle <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. where he commands ſubjection, &amp; forbids reſiſtence to the higher power, becauſe <hi>they are Gods ordinance, his Miniſters for praiſe to well-doers, for terrour to evill doers.</hi> But I muſt profeſſe my ſelf to diſſent from them in this opinion, conceiving that the Apoſtle in urging thoſe Reaſons drawne from the due ends of Power, doth intend to preſſe them to ſubjection by ſhewing them what benefit comes to men by authority in its due uſe; and not to ſhew them how far they are bound to be ſubject, and in what caſes they may reſiſt: For had he ſuch a meaning at that time, when the Governours did altogether croſſe thoſe ends of their Ordination, he had taught them rather a Doctrine of Reſiſtence then Subjection: ſhall we conceive that hee would preſſe ſubjection to Powers in the hands of Heathens and Perſecutors, if he had not intended they ſhould paſſively be ſubject unto them, even under thoſe Perſecutions? Rather I approve the received Doctrine of the Saints in ancient and moderne times, who could never finde this licence in that place of the Apoſtle: and doe concurre with Maſter <hi>Burroughs,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Anſw. to Dr. <hi>Ferne</hi> Sect. <hi>2.</hi>
                     </note> profeſſing againſt reſiſtence of au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, though abuſed: <hi>If thoſe</hi> (ſaies he) <hi>who have power to make Lawes, make ſinfull Lawes, and ſo give authority to any to force obedience we ſay here there muſt be either flying, or paſsive Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence.</hi> And againe, <hi>We acknowledge we muſt not reſiſt for Religion, if the Lawes of the land be againſt it.</hi> But what doe they ſay a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt this? In making ſuch Lawes againſt Religion the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates are not Gods ordinance; and therefore to reſiſt is not to reſiſt Gods ordinance: As an inferiour Magiſtrate, who hath a Commiſſion of Power for ſuch ends, is reſiſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble if hee exceed his Commiſſion, and abuſe his Power for other ends; ſo Princes being Gods Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, and having a deputed Commiſſion from him to ſuch ends, <hi>viz.</hi> the promotion of godlineſſe, Peace, Juſtice, if they pervert their power to contrary ends, may be reſiſted with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:155920:36"/>
violation of Gods ordinance. That I may give a ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factory anſwere to this, which is the ſumme of their long diſcourſe, I muſt lay it downe in ſeverall Aſſertions.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, I acknowledge Gods ordinance is not onely Power,<label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Aſſert. </seg>1</label> but Power for ſuch ends, <hi>ſc.</hi> the good of the People.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, it is alſo Gods ordinance, that there ſhould be <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Aſſert. </seg>2</label> in men, by publike conſent called thereto, and inveſted there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, a power to chooſe the meanes, the Lawes, and Rules of government conducing to that end: and a power of Judging in relation to thoſe Lawes, who be the well doers which ought to be praiſed, and who the evill doers who ought to be puniſhed. This is as fully Gods ordinance as the former; for without this the other cannot be performed.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, when they who have this finall civill Judicature <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Aſſert. </seg>3</label> ſhall cenſure good men as evill doers; or eſtabliſh iniquity by a Law, to the encouragement of evill doers; in this caſe, if it be a ſubordinate Magiſtrate doth it, appeale muſt bee made (as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> did) to the ſupreme; if it be the ſupreme, which through miſtake or corruption doth miſ-cenſure, from whom there lyes no Civill Appeale, then without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtence of that Judgement wee muſt paſſively ſubmit: And he who in his owne knowledge of innocency or goodneſſe of his cauſe ſhall by force reſiſt, that man erects a Tribunal in his owne heart againſt the Magiſtrates Tribunal; cleares himſelfe by a private Judgement againſt a publike, and exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutes his owne ſentence by force againſt the Magiſtrates ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, which hee hath repealed and made void in his owne heart. In unjuſt Cenſures by the higheſt Magiſtrate, from whom there is no Appeale but to God, the ſentence cannot be oppoſed till God reverſe it to whom we have appealed: In the meane time vvee muſt ſuffer, as Chriſt did, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding his Appeale, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.23. and ſo muſt wee notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding our Appeale, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4 19. for he did ſo for our ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample. If an Appeale to God, or a cenſure in the Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the condemned might give him power of reſiſtence, none would be guilty, or ſubmit to the Magiſtrates cenſure any further <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hen they pleaſe. I deſire thoſe Authors, before they ſettle their judgement in ſuch grounds (which I feare
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:155920:37"/>
will bring too much ſcandall) to weigh theſe particulars. Firſt, their opinion takes away from the Magiſtrate the chiefe part of Gods ordinance, <hi>ſc.</hi> povver of definitive judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Lawes and Perſons, who are the good, and who the bad, to be held ſo in Civill proceedings. Secondly, they ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie the Conſcience of Papiſts, Heretickes, and groſſeſt Malefactors to reſiſt the Magiſtrate, in caſe they be perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded their cauſe is good. Thirdly, they draw men off from the commands of Patience under perſecution, and conform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to Chriſt and his Apoſtles, in their patient enduring without verball or reall oppoſition, though Chriſt could not have wanted power to have done it, as he tells <hi>Peter.</hi> Fourthly, they deprive the Primitive and Moderne Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs of the glory of ſuffering, imputing it either to their ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance or diſability. Fifthly, it is a wonder, that ſith in Chriſts and his Apoſtles time there was ſo much uſe of this power of reſiſtence, they would by no expreſſe word ſhew the Chriſtians this liberty, but condemne reſiſtence ſo ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verely. Sixthly, there is in the caſe of the Parliament now taking up Armes no need of theſe offenſive grounds; Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on being now a part of our Nationall Law, and cannot ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer but the Law muſt ſuffer with it.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>2</label> Now to the propoſed Queſtion I anſwere, firſt Negatively, <hi>ſc.</hi> 1.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>1.</hi> When arms ought not to be aſſumed.</note> It ought not to be done againſt all illegall proceedings, but ſuch which are ſubverſive and unſufferable. Secondly, not publike reſiſtence, but in exceſſes inducing publike evils: for to repell private injuries of higheſt nature with publike hazzard and diſturbance, will not quit coſt, unleſſe in a pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate caſe the common Liberty be ſtrooke at. Thirdly, not when the government is actually ſubverted, and a new forme (though never ſo injuriouſly) ſet up, and the People already engaged in an Oath of abſolute ſubjection: for the remedy comes too late, and the eſtabliſhment of the new makes the former irrevocable by any juſtifiable power, within the compaſſe of that Oath of God: This was the caſe of the Senate of <hi>Rome</hi> in Saint <hi>Pauls</hi> time.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>2.</hi> When they may be aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med.</note> Secondly, affirmative<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: I conceive three caſes when the other Eſtates may law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:155920:37"/>
aſſume the force of the Kingdome, the King not joyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, or diſſenting, though the ſame be by Law committed to him. Firſt, when there is invaſion actually made, or immi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nently feared by a forraigne Power. Secondly, when by an inteſtine Faction the Lawes and Frame of government are ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretly undermined, or openly aſſaulted: In both theſe caſes the Being of the Government being endangered, their truſt binds, as to aſſiſt the King in ſecuring, ſo to ſecure it by themſelves, the King refuſing. In extreme neceſſities the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty of Voices cannot take place, neither ought a <hi>Negative Voice</hi> to hinder in this exigence, there being no freedome of deliberation and choice, when the Queſtion is about the laſt end: Their aſſuming the ſword in theſe caſes is for the King, whoſe Being (as King) depends on the Being of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome; and being interpretatively his act, is no diſparage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his Prerogative. Thirdly, in caſe the Fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall Rights of either of the three Eſtates bee invaded by one or both the reſt, the wronged may lawfully aſſume force for its owne defence; becauſe elſe it were not free, but depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent on the pleaſure of the other. Alſo the ſuppreſſion of either of them, or the diminiſhing of their Fundamentall Rights, carries with it the diſſolution of the Government: And therefore thoſe grounds which juſtifie force to preſerve its Being, allowes this caſe, which is a direct innovation of its Being and Frame.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. VII.</hi> Where the Legall Power of Finall judging in theſe caſes doth reſide,<note place="margin">Queſt. 7.</note> in caſe the three Eſtates differ about the ſame?</head>
                  <p>IN this Queſtion (for our more diſtinct proceeding) ſome <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>1</label> things are neceſſarily to be obſerved. Firſt,<note place="margin">The Queſtion ſtated.</note> that we med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle not here with the judicature of Queſtions of inferiour
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:155920:38"/>
nature, <hi>viz.</hi> ſuch as are 'twixt ſubject and ſubject, or the King and a ſubject, in matter of particular right, which may be decided other way, without detriment of the publike Frame, or diminution of the priviledges of either of the three Eſtates. Secondly difference is to be made even in the Queſtions of utmoſt danger: Firſt, for it may be alledged to be either from without, by invaſion of forrain Enemies; or by a confederacy of inteſtine ſubverters, in which neither of the three Eſtates are alledged to be intereſſed, and ſo the caſe may be judged without relation to either of them, or detri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to their priviledges. Here I conceive a greater lati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of power may be given to ſome to judge without the other; for it inferres not a ſubordinating of any of the three to the other. Secondly, or elſe it may be alledged by one or two of the Eſtates againſt the other, that not contenting it ſelfe with the Powers allowed to it by the Lawes of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, it ſeekes to ſwallow up, or entrench on the privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges of the other, either by immediate endevours, or elſe by protecting and intereſſing it ſelfe in the ſubverſive plots of other men. Thirdly, in this caſe wee muſt alſo diſtinguiſh betwixt, firſt, authority of raiſing Forces for defenſe againſt ſuch ſubverſion, being knowne and evident: ſecondly and authority of judging and finall determining, that the accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Eſtate is guilty of ſuch deſigne and endevour of ſubver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, when it is denied and proteſted againſt. This laſt is the particular in this Queſtion to be conſidered; not whether the People are bound to obey the authority of two, or one of the Legiſlative Eſtates in reſiſting the ſubverſive aſſaies of the other, being apparent and ſelf-evident; which I take in this Treatiſe to be cleare. But when ſuch plea of ſubverſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is more obſcure and queſtionable, which of the three Eſtates hath the power of ultime and ſupreme judicature by Vote or ſentence to determine it againſt the other; ſo that the People are bound to reſt in that determination, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly to give their aſſiſtance, <hi>eo nomine,</hi> becauſe it is by ſuch Power ſo noted and declared?<note place="margin">Determinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Queſtion.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>For my part in ſo great a cauſe, if my earneſt deſire of pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique good, and peace, may juſtifie me to deliver my minde,
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:155920:38"/>
I will preſcribe to the uery Queſtion: for it includes a ſole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſme in government of a mixt temperature: To demand which Eſtate may challenge this power of finall determina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Fundamentall controverſies ariſing betwixt them is to demand which of them ſhall be abſolute: For I conceive that in the firſt part hereof, I have made it good, that this fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall utmoſt controverſie ariſing betwixt the three Legiſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Eſtates, can have no legall, conſtituted Judge in a mixed government: for in ſuch difference, he who affirmes that the people are bound to follow the Judgement of the King a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt that of the Parliament, deſtroyes the mixture into abſoluteneſſe: And he who affirmes that they are bound to cleave to the Judgement of the two Houſes againſt that of the King, reſolves the Monarchie into an Ariſtocracie, or Democracie, according as he places this finall Judgement. Whereas I take it to be an evident truth, that in a mixed go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment no power is to be attributed to either Eſtate, which directly, or by neceſſary conſequence, deſtroyes the liberty of the other.</p>
                  <p>Yet it is ſtrange to ſee, how in this Epidemicall diviſion of <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>2</label> the Kingdome, the Abettors of both parts claime this un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conceſsible Judgement. But let us leave both ſides, pleading for that which we can grant neither, and weigh the ſtrength of their Arguments.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, Dr. <hi>Ferne</hi> layes downe two reaſons,<note place="margin">Diſſolution of Arguments placing it in the King.</note> why this finall Judgement ſhould belong to the King<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 1. Monarchie, ſaies he, <hi>Sect.</hi> 5. ſettles the chiefe power and finall Judgement in one. This <hi>Poſition</hi> of his can be abſolutely true no where but in abſolute Monarchies: and in effect, his book knowes no other then abſolute government. 2. Seeing ſome one muſt be truſted in every State, <hi>It is reaſon,</hi> ſaies he, <hi>Sect</hi> 5. <hi>the higheſt and finall truſt, ſhould be in the higher and Supreame power.</hi> I preſume by finall truſt, he meanes the truſt of determining theſe Supreame and finall diſagreements; and accordingly I anſwer; It is not neceſſary that any one be truſted with a binding power of Judicature in theſe caſes; for by the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations of this government, none is, yea, none can be truſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:155920:39"/>
with it: for to intend a mixed government, and yet to ſettle the laſt reſolution of all judgement in one, is to contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict their very intention. Neither in a conſtituted govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment muſt we diſpoſe of powers according to the gueſſe of our reaſon; for mens apprehenſions are various; The Dr. thinkes this power fitteſt for the King: His anſwerers judge it fitteſt for the two Houſes, and give their reaſons for it too. Powers muſt there reſide, where they are <hi>de facto</hi> by the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chitects of a government placed: he who can bring a funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentall Act ſtating this power in any, ſaies ſomething to the matter: but to give our conjectures, where it ſhould be, is but to provide fuell for contention.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Diſſolution of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>rguments placing it in the two Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes.</note>On the contrary, The Author of that which is called <hi>A Fuller Anſwer to that Dr.</hi> hath two maine Aſſertions placing this Judgement in the two Houſes.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. The finall and caſting reſult of this States Judgement concerning what theſe Lawes, dangers, and meanes of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention are, reſides in the two Houſes of Parliament, ſaies he, <hi>p.</hi> 10.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. In this finall reſolution of the States Judgement, the people are to reſt, <hi>ibidem, pag.</hi> 14. Good Lord! What ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tream oppoſition is between theſe two ſorts of men? If the maintenance of theſe extremes be the ground of this warre, then our Kingdome is miſerable, and our Government loſt which ſide ſoever overcome: for I have, more then once, made it good, that theſe Aſſertions are deſtructive on both ſides: But I am rather perſwaded, that theſe Officious Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugners overdoe their worke, and give more to them whoſe cauſe they plead, then they ever intended to aſſume: Nay, rather give to every one their due: give no power to one of theſe three to cruſh and undoe the other at pleaſure: But why doth this Anſwer give all that to the two Houſes which ere while they would not ſuffer when the Judges in the caſe of Ship-money had given it to the King? ſure when they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied it to him they did not intend it to themſelves. 1. Hee tells us In them reſides the reaſon of the State: And that the ſame reaſon and Judgement of the State which firſt gave this government its being, and conſtitution; therefore
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:155920:39"/>
all the people are to be led by it and ſubmit to it as their pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique reaſon and Judgement.</p>
                  <p>I anſwer, If by ſtate, he meane the whole Kingdome: I ſay, the reaſon of the two Houſes divided from the King, is not the reaſon of the Kingdome, for it is not the Kings rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, who is the head and chiefe in the Kingdome. If by ſtate be meant the people, then it muſt be granted, that as farre forth as they repreſent them, their reaſon is to be accounted the reaſon of the Kingdome: and doth binde ſo farre forth as the publique reaſon of the Kingdome can binde after they have reſtrained their reaſon and will to a condition of ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection: ſo that put caſe it be the reaſon of the ſtate, yet not the ſame which firſt gave this Government its being: for then it was the reaſon of a State, yet free and to uſe their reaſon and Judgement in ordaining a Government: but now the reaſon of a State bound by Oath to a Government, and not at liberty to reſolve againe: Or to aſſume a ſupreme pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of judging, diſtructive to the frame of Government they have eſtabliſhed, and reſtrained themſelves unto Their rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon is ours, ſo farre as they are an ordained repreſentative body: But I have before demonſtrated, that in this frame, the Houſes could not be ordained a legall Tribunall to paſſe Judgement in this laſt caſe: for then the Architects by gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving them that Judicature, had ſubordinated the King to them, and ſo had conſtituted no Monarchie. 2. He argues, the Parliament being the Court of ſupreme Judicature and the Kings great and higheſt Councell, therefore that is not to be denied to it, which inferiour Courts ordinarily have power to do, <hi>viz</hi> To judge matters of right betweene the King and Subject: Yea, in the higheſt caſe of all: The Kings power to tax the ſubject in caſe of danger, and his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſole Judge of that danger, was brought to cognizance, and paſſed by the Judges in the Exchequor. I anſwer, 1. There is not the ſame reaſon betwixt the Parliament &amp; other courts. In theſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>he King is Judge, the Judges being deputed by him, and judging by his authority; ſo that if any of his Rights be tried before them, it is his owne Judgement, and he judges himſelfe; and therefore it is fit he ſhould be bound
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:155920:40"/>
by his owne ſentence: But in Parliament the King and Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple are Judges, and that not by an authority derived from him, but originally inveſted in themſelves. So that when the two Eſtates judge without him in any caſe not prejudged by him, it cannot be called his Judgement, (as that of the other Courts, being done by his authority) and if he be bound by any Judgment of the two Eſtates without him, he is bound by an externall power which is not his owne; that is, he is ſubordinated to another power in the State where he is ſupreme; which is contradictory. Secondly, in other Courts, if any caſe of right be judged 'twixt him and the ſubject, they are caſes of particular Rights which diminiſh not Royalty if determined againſt him. Or if they paſſe caſes of generall right, (as they did in that of Ship-money) it is but declaratively to ſhew what is by Law due to one and the other: yet their Judgement is revocable, and liable to a repeale by a ſuperiour Court, as that was by Parliament. But if the Kings Prerogatives ſhould be ſubjected to the Judgement of the two Eſtates, the King diſſenting, then he ſhould be ſubject to a ſentence in the higheſt Court, and ſo irremediable; a Judicatory ſhould be ſet up to determine of his higheſt Rights without him, from which he could have no remedy. Thus maine cauſes may bee alledged, why, though other Courts doe judge his Rights, yet the two Eſtates in Parliament (without him) cannot: and it is from no defect in their power, but rather from the eminency of it, that they cannot. If one deputed by common conſent of three, doth by the power they have given them determine controverſies betweene thoſe three, it is not for either of them to challenge right to judge thoſe caſes, becauſe one who is inferiour to them doth it. Indeed if the power of the two Houſes were a deputed power, as the power of other Courts is, this Argument were of good ſtrength: but they being concurrents in a ſupreme Court by a power originally their owne, I conceive it hard to put the power of finall Judgement in all controverſies 'twixt Him and them exclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſively, or ſolely into their hands.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="73" facs="tcp:155920:40"/>If it be demanded then, how this cauſe can be decided?<label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>3</label> and which way muſt the People turne in ſuch a contention?<note place="margin">What be done in ſuch a Contention?</note> I anſwere, If the non-deciſion be tolerable, it muſt remaine undecided, whiles the Principle of legall deciſion is thus di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided, and by that diviſion each ſuſpends the others power. If it be ſuch as is deſtructive, and neceſſitates a determinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, this muſt be made evident; and then every Perſon muſt aide that Part, which in his beſt Reaſon and Judgement ſtands for publike good, againſt the deſtructive. And the Lawes and Government which he ſtands for, and is ſworne to juſtifies and beares him out in it, yea; bindes him to it. If any wonder I ſhould juſtifie a power in the two Houſes to reſiſt, and command aide againſt any Agents of deſtructive commands of the King, and yet not allow them power of judging when thoſe Agents or commands are deſtructive. I anſwere, I doe not ſimply deny them power of judging and declaring this; but I deny them to be a legall Court ordained to judge of this caſe authoritatively, ſo as to bind all People to receive and reſt in their judgement for conſcience of its authority, and becauſe they have Voted it: 'Tis the evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, not the power of their Votes, muſt bind our Reaſon and Practice in this caſe: We ought to conceive their Votes the Diſcoveries made by the beſt eyes of the Kingdome and which in likelihood ſhould ſee moſt: But when they Vote a thing againſt the proceedings of the Third and ſupreme E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate, our Conſciences muſt have evidence of Truth to guide them, and not the ſole authority of Votes; and that for the Reaſon ſo oft alledged.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="8" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. VIII.</hi> The contention now in being is debated, and the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dieſt meanes of Reconcilement propoſed.</head>
                  <p>THus have I (for my owne ſatisfaction, and the Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>1</label> of every moderate and impartiall man who will
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:155920:41"/>
peruſe the ſame) ſet downe what I verily conceive to be the truth concerning thoſe high matters, firſt of Monarchy in generall, and then of this of England, and have given my de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termination concerning all the weighty Queſtions which ariſe conſiderable in the courſe of handling both: Now no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing remaines, but to reſolve the Conſcience by this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedent light, what to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>udge of the unhappy contention, which now is broken out into open warre, betweene the King and the two Houſes. But this depending on matter of fact, is more fitly referred to every mans owne memory and Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; and nothing is to be done, but to acquaint himſelfe with the certaine truth of thoſe matters of fact, and then to judge therof according to the former Rules. To this iſſue the whole controverſie is brought, <hi>That the two Houſes may law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully reſiſt by force of Armes, all counſells and attempts of what men ſoever, tending to the ſubverſion of the eſtabliſhed Frame of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or themſelves and their Fundamentall Priviledges;</hi> which is equivalent to the other; yea, though they are warranted by <hi>the commands and perſonall preſence of the King himſelfe:</hi> And that clearly, this is no reſiſtence of the higher power in our Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment (ſo no force be intended or uſed againſt the Kings owne Perſon) nor doth it come within the cenſure of Saint <hi>Paul Rom.</hi> 13. nor any other Scripture, nor right Reaſon grounded thereon: ſo that the Conſcience aſſured hereof, hath nothing elſe to doe but to enquire whether the truth of Factlyes either in the Affirmative of the two Houſes; <hi>That the Kingdome was in imminent danger, the King refuſing to joyne with them for prevention of it, when they aſſumed the</hi> Militia <hi>for defence:</hi> Or elſe in the Kings Negative. Much hath beene ſaid on both ſides, to draw the Conſciences of men to adhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence; and many (no doubt) have judged according to their pre ingaged affections: Many Papers have I ſeene running out on both ſides to unjuſtifiable extremes, and have much holpen on the contention, by making the breach wider: yea, I have read more ſaid for them then (I am perſwaded, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the heat of the contention) either will ſay for <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>2</label> themſelves, or can without the ſubverſion of the other.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">A debate upon the contention.</note>Now for a man to reſolve his Conſcience about the law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:155920:41"/>
or unlawfulneſſe of this Warre, the courſe is not to cry it downe indefinitely, as a Reſiſtence of Gods ordinance, nor of the higher Power: Nor to juſtifie it, becauſe the cauſe ſtood for is Religion, and expurgation of in-crept cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions in Church and State: For all ſtanding for Religion and Reformation is not a juſtifiable cauſe to take up Armes; we having proved it before, that in this Kingdome nothing can warrant it, but apparent danger from deſtructive Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellours and Inſtruments. Neither is it enough to demand, as Doctor <hi>Ferne</hi> doth <hi>Sect</hi> 6. <hi>Who were first in Armes?</hi> for the other part will by their Almanack finde Armes and Forces gathered and employed before thoſe in Hull:<note place="margin">Declar. of the Lords and Commons of Apr <hi>3. 1642.</hi>
                     </note> but that is not the reſolving enquiry; it may fall out the defenſive part may be firſt in Armes, to prevent the ruine of counſells and Plots which are apparently contrived, but not executed. The re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolving enquiry (I thinke) muſt be, <hi>Whether at the Parliaments taking up of Armes, the Common-wealth, Frame of eſtabliſhed Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, or</hi> (which is all one) <hi>the Being and radicall Powers of Parliament were in apparent danger of ſubverſion?</hi> For if ſo, then the Armes and Force uſed againſt the Counſellours or Agents thereof is proved lawfull by all the precedent diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe.</p>
                  <p>Now it will be alledged, and is in part acknowledged,<note place="margin">His Majeſties Anſw. to the Petit. of the houſes March <hi>26. 1642.</hi>
                     </note> that there was a grand intention and plot of altering the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of this Kingdome, and reducing it to an arbitrary way. They will not ſay his Majeſtie was conſcious of it; but it was aimed at by many about him, and in power with him, whom it concerned to have him abſolute: By theſe men he was told that ſuch things were Law, which if they had bin ſo, then he had bin abſolute by law. They will inſtance in the long and purpoſed diſuſe of Parliaments: The arbitrary Taxes and Impoſitions on moſt of the Commodities of the Kingdome: The encroachnent of the Arbitrary Courts up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Legall: The Impoſition of Ship-money: And the Judges opinion that the King had power to tax the ſubject in times of danger, and that he is the ſole Judge of that dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger: The raiſing an Army, and forcing the ſubject to furniſh the ſame with Coat and Conduct-money. The intention of
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:155920:42"/>
bringing up the Army, to ſubvert, or at beſt, to awe and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fine the Parliament to bounds of proceeding of their owne ſetting. All this before or upon the beginning of the Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament. Then the evidences and proofes againſt the Earle of <hi>Strafford,</hi> His Majeſties comming with the terror of ſuch an attendance into the Houſe of Commons, to demand ſuch a number of Members. Here is a ſucceſsion of deſignes, all before the leaſt ſhew of reſiſtence: for his Majeſties com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming to the Houſe was <hi>Iannuary</hi> 4. 1641. And the firſt Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to his Majeſtie about the <hi>Militia</hi> was not till the 26. of the ſame: And their reſolution to ſettle it by themſelves, His Majeſties refuſing was not till <hi>March</hi> 1. And among all theſe there is not one but tends to deſtroy the frame of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment. Not that every one who had a hand in them did aime at ſuch a deſtruction; but looking on the deſigne it ſelfe (and we muſt judge of mens intentions by the nature of their Counſells and enterprizes,) every one of them ſtrikes at the foundation of this legall frame, and tends to the introducti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Abſoluteneſſe and Arbitrarineſſe in the Soveraigne.</p>
                  <p>I acknowledge, that ſince that time, there is a Plea on both ſides of danger of ſubverſion: The King withdrew from <hi>London:</hi> and oft affirmes that <hi>He was driven thence,</hi> and could no longer remaine in ſafety: And the two Houſes on the former deſignes plead a danger of ſubverſion from evill Counſellours. Both ſides now complaine of danger, and have taken up Armes to repell that danger: but theſe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints of danger, and taking up of Armes by both ſides, was all ſince the ſucceſſion of thoſe fore-recited plots. I know what hath been intended or done ſince the taking of Armes may be all affirmed to be for defenſe againſt danger; the withdrawment of ſo many Members of both Houſes, the acts of hoſtility on both ſides, the taxing, ſpoyling, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doing of thouſands of innocent people, all muſt be excuſed by neceſſity of Warre, and ſelf-defenſe. But what can be ſaid for all thoſe Plots and Eſſaies, which were the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments firſt grounds of Feares and Forces? Were they remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved before they tooke up Armes, and ſo their aſſuming them made cauſleſſe and inexcuſable? You will ſay, Thoſe were
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:155920:42"/>
the Plots of men in grace and authority about His Majeſty, and that the illegality of thoſe proceedings being made knowne to him, He diſclaimes them profeſſing ſolemnly he hath no intent but to governe by Law; and acknowledges that the Law is the meaſure of his power. But they doe tell you, That they object nothing againſt his Majeſty, they im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute nothing to Him, nor uſe force againſt Him, but thoſe deſtructive Counſellours, and their Abbettors which are about Him; becauſe their danger is not from His intenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, but from theirs. It is anſwered, that His Majeſty of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers to ſecure them, the Lawes, Liberties, and Religion, by any Acts they ſhall deviſe to that purpoſe.<note place="margin">Parliam. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrance May <hi>19. 1642</hi>
                     </note> They will tell you, Their danger is not from want of Laws to ſecure them, for they are ſecured by Law already; their danger is from Men, and their Plots and Deſignes to overthrow Law; and a danger of ſubverſion of Law cannot bee ſecured by Law; ſucceeding Lawes can be no better nor ſtronger then former Lawes: ſo that where thoſe men and their counſels are in power, whoſe aime hath been the ſubverſion of Parliaments, Liberties, and Lawes; and thoſe Doctrines remaine affirm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and maintained by the Clergie of that ſide, which ſubvert all limitations of Monarchy, make all Lawes Acts of grace, and revocable Immunities granted to Subjects; condemning for Rebellion all force uſed even by the Parliament it ſelfe, againſt the meaneſt Inſtruments of violence employed by the Princes Will; making the Princes Will and Gods Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance one and the ſame thing, of the ſame latitude; ſo that reſiſtence of one is reſiſtence of the other: ſuch Counſellours and ſuch Doctrines are (they ſay) the ground of publike danger, from which no Lawes but Juſtice can ſecure us. Publike Liberty and Power of forcible reſiſtence of Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of ſervitude are ſo conjoyned, that if you make it un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull ſimply to uſe ſuch power of reſiſtence, you make it unlawfull for a People to be free.</p>
                  <p>What courſe then can be ſufficient to anſwere their De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>3</label> of ſafety, if Lawes cannot doe it?<note place="margin">Meanes of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>concilement propoſed.</note> Though I incurre the cenſure of high Preſumption, yet I will be ſo bold to af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:155920:43"/>
my opinion herein, ſubmitting it to the cenſure of every Judicious Reader; wiſhing it were worthy to be ſcanned by thoſe, in whoſe hands it is to heale our diviſions. What ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt heart doth not bleed, to ſee the ruine of this late flouri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing Kingdome goe on ſo faſt? Who can doe other then ſpeake his minde, who conceives hee thinkes of any thing which may conduce to Peace and the re-uniting of this di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided Body? Suffer mee therefore to diſcloſe my heart in a caſe, in which every good man hath a deep intereſt. Thus then I could heartily deſire.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Petit. </seg>1</label> Firſt, that the Parliament would deſire and ſeeke in this unuſuall way of Force, no more then what makes neceſſari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for their, and the publike ſecurity: for none can juſtifie force in them, any further then for ſecurity of their Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges, Lawes, and frame of Government.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Petit. </seg>2</label>
                     <note place="margin">Anſw. to the Petition of Commons Ian. <hi>28. 1641.</hi>
                     </note>Secondly, that His Majeſty would be pleaſed (according to his gracious Reſolution, <hi>viz. To deny onely thoſe things, the granting whereof would alter the Fundamentall Lawes, and endan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger the foundation on which publike happineſſe is built:</hi>) to conde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcend to all Acts of ſafety, both by eſtabliſhing of Lawes ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to it; and removall of Perſons of deſtructive counſells and Judgements, becauſe the danger alledged is from ſuch.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Petit. </seg>3</label> Thirdly, that becauſe their maine feare hath been, that while his Majeſty is ſwayed by ſuch Perſons, whoſe Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and endevours have been for Abſoluteneſſe, the <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litia</hi> of the Kingdome may be by them (making uſe of his Majeſties Authority) employed in bringing to paſſe their long fomented, and not yet deſerted deſigne; His Majeſty would be pleaſed (for this preſent) to authorize ſuch over the <hi>Militia</hi> whom the Houſes ſhall approve of, not thereby diſparaging his power over the <hi>Militia,</hi> which by Law is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſted in him; but ſatisfying by a condeſcent of grace their Feares from apprehenſions of preſent danger.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Petit. </seg>4</label> Fourthly, that the two Houſes (in their wiſedom) would put a difference between thoſe Perſons who were the anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>linquents, Contrivers, and principall Agents in the former deſignes of Arbitrarineſſe; and thoſe Members of both Houſes; who ſince the Kings with-drawment, and their
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:155920:43"/>
aſſuming the <hi>Militia,</hi> have gone from the Houſes to ſerve and adhere to his Majeſty: For ſince the time that both parts have declared themſelves to be in danger, many good ſubjects and Patriots have followed the parts, from conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and perſwaſion of the truth of Allegations on either ſide, as their care and opinion of either Part hath lead them; (not that I can acquit them, who on any miſ-leading aſſiſt the deſtructive party, from guilt, as Acceſſaries and Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of ſo unnaturall a deſigne) but that I cannot ſee how the authority and freedome of either of the three Eſtates can chooſe but undergoe a ſhew of diſparagement, if its ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herents and propugners (when it cries out of danger of ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion from the other, and calls and requires their aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance) ſhould be proceeded againſt and puniſhed as Delin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quents, when they profeſſe their aime hath beene no more then to preſerve the juſt rights of any of the fundamentall Eſtates of the Kingdom, without impairment of the other.</p>
                  <p>Fifthly that if poſſible, all thoſe might be re-admitted in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Petit. </seg>5</label> their ſeverall Houſes, which are not guilty of the former deſignes for Abſoluteneſſe, and have nothing alledged againſt them but their adherence to the King in this diviſion, and might fit and act ſecurely there, according to the due free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of their Houſes.</p>
                  <p>Sixthly, that his Majeſty (for the ſake of Peace, and preſent <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Petit. </seg>6</label> neceſſity of compoſing this diſtemperature) would be plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to put himſelfe upon the Judgment and Affection of the two Eſtates ſo aſſembled in their full Bodies and ſuſpend the uſe of his <hi>Negative voice,</hi> reſolving to give his royall aſſent to what ſhall paſſe by the <hi>major</hi> part of both Houſes freely vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, concerning all matters of grievance and difference now depending in the two Houſes. I am confident, if ever this War be tranſacted without the ruine of one ſide, which will endanger, if not undoe the whole, it muſt be by ſome ſuch way of remiſſion of rigour on both ſides as I have now de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed: <hi>Which the God of Peace, in whoſe hands are the hearts and counſels of men, ſpeedily and graciouſly effect for his Name ſake.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
